<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A suruey of the apostasy of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, sometyme Arch-bishop of Spalato. / Drawne out his owne booke, and written in Latin, by Fidelis Annosus, Verementanus Druinus, deuine: and translated into English by A. M.</title>
            <title>Survey of the apostasy of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, sometyme Arch-bishop of Spalato</title>
            <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852707</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1234:16, 1236:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A suruey of the apostasy of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, sometyme Arch-bishop of Spalato. / Drawne out his owne booke, and written in Latin, by Fidelis Annosus, Verementanus Druinus, deuine: and translated into English by A. M.</title>
                  <title>Survey of the apostasy of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, sometyme Arch-bishop of Spalato</title>
                  <author>Floyd, John, 1572-1649.</author>
                  <author>Hawkins, Henry, 1571?-1646.</author>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624. Archiepiscopus Spalatensis, suæ profectionis consilium exponit. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 146, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XVII.[1617]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Fidelis Annosus = John Floyd.</note>
                  <note>A.M. = Henry Hawkins.</note>
                  <note>The passages from de Dominis are translated directly from the Latin original:  Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archiepiscopus Spalatensis, suæ profectionis consilium exponit (STC 6996).</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 7008.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 7008 on UMI microfilm reel 1234.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1566-1624 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SVRVEY OF THE APOSTASY OF MARCVS ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS, Sometyme Arch-bishop of SPALATO.</p>
            <p>Drawne out his owne Booke, and written in Latin, by <hi>Fidelis Annoſus, Veremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus Druinus,</hi> Deuine: AND Tranſlated into English by A.M.</p>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. M.DC.XVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:2"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOVR to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader, I wiſh thee to peruſe this Treatiſe with the ſame mind and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction wherwith it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. We make triall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by whole ſome admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s we can reclay me an Apoſtata, by order a Prieſt, in dignity an Arch-biſhop, and (to vſe no worſe tearmes) by nature, and in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners a Man, ſinning out of human leuity and folly.</p>
            <p>We would not arraigne him vpon other mens euidence; but make him (a courſe moſt reaſonable) both Plantiſſe and Defendant in his owne cauſe, and the Holy Scriptures, with the ancient Fathers, his Iudges: To whoſe Sentence and Authority if he yield, we will entertaine with ioy his Returne, whoſe Flight, and Apoſtaſy we now commiſerate. But if feare of ſhame be more forcible with him, then loue of Truth; if he will be ſtubborne in his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and obdurate in his ſinnes; he ſhall periſh to himſelfe: an example for others to beware, and a meanes of ſaluation of many.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:3"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOVR to the Reader.</head>
            <p>I Thought good to let thee vnderſtand (Courteous Reader) that the Authour of this <hi>Suruey,</hi> in citing the pages of the Arch-bishops Booke, followeth the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Edition, printed for <hi>Iohn Bill.</hi> The wordes of the Arch-bishop I haue endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to tranſlate faithfully into English, and haue not followed the ſuppoſed English Tranſlation, which indeed is no tranſlation at all, but a vayne and idle ſtorish vpon the matter, many times very oppoſite to the Text, darke, and without ſenſe; in ſo much that it may ſeeme the Tranſlatour therof ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did not vnderſtand well the Latin ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, or was ashamed at the true conceits of his Arch-hishop, and therfore would not ſet them forth in English.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177851:3"/>
            <head>A SVRVEY OF THE APOSTASY OF MARCVS ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS, Sometimes Archbishop of SPALATO. Drawne out of his owne Booke,</head>
            <byline>by Fidelis Annoſus Verementanus Druinus.</byline>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O ſooner was your Booke, <hi>Marke Antony,</hi> deliuered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands by a friend of mine, wherein you ſet downe the purpoſe of your going, but I preſently peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it. I expected from ſuch an Apoſtata ſome new and colourable reaſons of reuolte from the Catholike Church. When I found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vulgar excuſes, vſurped by ancient
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177851:4"/>Heretikes of all ages, growne (by long vſage) worne, &amp; thred bare, I could not but wonder at your Proiect, how you could perſwade your ſelfe, that with a few, ſilly, and ill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted leaues, a wickednes, of all others the greateſt and fowleſt, could ſo eaſily be ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And not only you bring nothing wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to excuſe your crime, but ſo vnwarily and groſſely you diſcouer your ſelfe, that from the ſteps left printed in your booke, the whole race of your Apoſtaſy may not only be traced and tracked out, but fully ſhaped forth. It is needleſſe therfore for him that would know you, to ſeeke out matters a far off, or to liſten to rumors, euer vncertaine and often falſe. The Rat by his owne ſauour is ſufficiently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed: out of your owne booke may be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered inough, and too much, to declare <hi>Who you were, and who now you are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From hence haue I taken an Inuentory of your Apoſtaſy, to the publiſhing wherof foure cauſes haue moued me. Firſt, leaſt with the vaine titulary ſound wherewith you ſet your ſelfe forth in the front of your booke any be deceaued, to thinke that which <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> writeth ſhould not be true:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul. de praeſc. ca.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>That thoſe are not to be eſteemed prudent, nor faithfull, nor lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whome hereſies can peruert.</hi> The ſecond, that by this your example, others may become more wary in following your ſtepps whoſe fal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177851:4"/>ſo deſeruedly they dread to behold. Thirdly, that the Engliſh Proteſtants may learne to be aſhamed, to glory ſo much in you whome ouer greedily they admitted, with promiſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues you would proue a fatall writer againſt <hi>Rome.</hi> They that know you, what will they ſay? Doubtles, that one of weake ſight may raigne amongſt the blind; that beggers haue nothing but a few ragges to boaſt of; that men are eaſily perſwaded that ſhall come to paſſe which earneſtly they deſire. The fourth cauſe concerneth your ſelfe, who may reape this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant fruite out of this Suruey, to <hi>know your ſelfe.</hi> The ſpeciall end of my writing is your ſaluation. Should not I write for him for whome Chriſt died? ſhould I ſpare my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of writing for you, when God of ſheding his bloud for you made no end, but with his life? Peruſe then with a quiet mind what cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity hath ſuggeſted: regard not how ſharpe the things are which you read, but how true, how authentically proued, God being the Iudge, your owne conſcience giuing euidence. Your diſeaſe will not permit, that I ſhould deale coldly, or diſſemble with you: it hath wrought into the in moſt parts of your body, it hath diſperſed it ſelfe into the bowells, nor could I ſearch into it, lurking in the quick, without your payne and feeling.</p>
            <p>Strong muſt the medicines be that muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177851:5"/>cure you. And nothing is ſtronger then the Truth, nothing more wholeſome to a man then the knowledge of himſelfe, the roote of all euill and errours being not to know ones ſelf. Chriſt threatens that Paſtour who knows not himſelfe, with the penalty of Apoſtaſy, which of all other is the greateſt. <hi>If thou knoweſt not thy ſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>go forth and follow after the ſteppes of thy flockes, and feed thy kids beſides the tabernacles of the Paſtours.</hi> Which place S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> moſt elegantly declareth, and ſo, as he may ſeeme plainly to ſpeake vnto you.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 40.</note> 
               <hi>If you know not your ſelfe</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>go your wayes, I do not caſt you forth; but get you hence, that thoſe which are within may ſay vnto you; he went out from vs, but he was not of vs. Go treade you the footing of your flockes, not of one flock, but of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and wandring flockes. Go feed your goates, not like to Peter, to whome it is ſaid, feed my ſheep. Go feed your goates in the ſhepheards tabernacle, not in the paſtures where is one flock &amp; one Paſtour.</hi> That this puniſhment is inflicted on your ſelf, if you haue not loſt togeather with faith all ſenſe &amp; reaſon, you cannot but acknowledg. We truly haue not thruſt you out, but freely you went forth of your ſelfe. Scarce had you departed, when you lighted vpon ſteps &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers path-wayes of doctrine Lutheran, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinian, Zuinglian, Anabaptiſtcall, Arian, different and oppoſite one to another. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177851:5"/>further, you arriue not to the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of one Paſtour, but to the ſhep-heards Tentes, being not ſo much for the number of perſons as for variety of opinions, many. Wherfore now at laſt looke back, by what gate you entred into theſe miſchiefes you knew not your ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Had you but known your ſelfe, you would neuer haue imagined, much leſſe haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſixt page of your booke, <hi>I am not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to auerre, that I was had in as much eſteeme in our Prouinces &amp; Churches, as any other.</hi> Modeſty requires, that men ſhould be baſhfull in ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, though with great moderation, things tending to their owne praiſe: whereas you proclayme your ſelfe ſecond to none of the Biſhops, either of the State of Venice, or of the Catholike world beſides, and this you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to ſpeake without bluſhing You ſay true; Shamefaſtnes is not wont to wayt vpon an Apoſtata. But we, howſoeuer you dreame of your being famous, had newes of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Spalato</hi> his flight, before we heard of his name. <hi>Marke Antony</hi> in the Northerne parts was ſooner knowne by his face then by his fame; he came ſo faſt, that he preuented the meſſenger of his worth and eſtimation. The fugitiue Primate himſelfe firſt declared to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that there was any ſuch Spalatian Primate. Notwithſtanding you were not more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177851:6"/>to the world then to your ſelf, which is the cauſe you inſolently prefixe your name to your booke, as already knowne and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to giue it luſtre, <hi>Marke Antony de Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Archbiſhop of Spalato, ſets downe the reaſon of his going.</hi> So you ſtile your booke, as if you were the Pithian Apollo ready to giue Oracles, or ſome Dictator deliuering Lawes vnto the people, or Pithagoras preſcribing to his ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Aphoriſmes, or at leaſt ſome Authour knowne by his former writings able to gaine credit to any worke by the ſplendour of his name. Who, notwithſtanding, were at that time (for afterwards you became more noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious through the ſtaine of your fall) ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, that many wondred at the title, nor were there wanting inquirers, who ſhould this <hi>Marke Antony</hi> be? What going is that he ſpeakes of ſo vncertainly, without naming either whither, or from whence? Is peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that old <hi>Marke Antony</hi> reuiued againe, and fled from Rome to Aegipt? that <hi>Antony</hi> ſo famous for wine and venery, who hauing violated his former faith to his Roman ſpouſe no leſſe renowned for chaſtity then noble of blood, ioyned himſelfe to that Aegiptian wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man infamous for her many foule enormities: Thus did men, not yet acquainted with your iourney, deſcant vpon the title of your booke, framing coniectures of the authour of <hi>Marke
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177851:6"/>Antonyes</hi> name. They could not ſpeake more aſſuredly of a perſon wholy vnknowne, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did their rouing diſcourſes much miſſe of the marke. For you hauing left the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Spouſe, and violated your firſt faith, haue matched your ſelfe to that Lutheran brat, who being of her Fathers condition, <hi>no more able to refrayne from venery, then from food,</hi> differs not much from Cleopatra's manners. If you but reſemble that drunken Triumuir as well in life, as you do in name, by this match may that old ſaying be renewed, <hi>Bacchus is wedded to Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177851:7"/>
               <head>THE FIRST PART OF THE SVRVEY OF APOSTASY, or the Ladder of <hi>Marke Antonies</hi> fall, conſiſting of eight ſteps, or degrees.</head>
               <p>SINCE therfore you muſt be cured by the moſt true knowledge of your ſelfe, who through your too high a conceite of your ſelfe, haue ſlid downe into hell in this Suruey, I put you in mind of your ſelfe, whom your ſelfe haue ſo much forgot, and I lay open your Apoſtaſy, not ſo much to the Readers eye, that he ſhould deteſt it, as before your owne conſcience that you may bewayle it. Behould now at laſt, who you were when you ſeemed a Catholike, and by what ſtepps by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle &amp; litle you fell into this abyſſe. The degrees therfore are theſe, <hi>ſecret Pride, cloſe Infidelity, ſuſpicious Lightnes, abandoning the Ieſuites Order, ambition of holy Dignities, audacious Contention for Preheminence, open Contumacy againſt the Pope,</hi> finally <hi>Preſumption of your owne iudgment and learning aboue the Church.</hi> I will handle all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177851:7"/>theſe in their order, not led by variable rumors but by euident arguments, and for the moſt part taken out of your owne Booke.</p>
               <div n="1" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt degree,</hi> Secret Pride.</head>
                  <p>HERESIES are in number diuers, deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by nations, but much more by man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, rites, and errours amongſt themſelues: <hi>Yet all are ſiſters</hi> (ſaith S Auguſtin) <hi>borne of the ſelf ſame mother Pride.</hi> To which purpoſe ſaith S. Gregory, <hi>Pride is the ſeat of Heretickes, for were they not firſt puffed vp in their owne conceipt they would neuer fall into ſtrife of peruerſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> This alſo, <hi>Antony,</hi> was the beginning of al your miſchiefe long agoe: through a certaine ſecret Pride you coueted to ſhew your ſelfe wiſe, and zealous, for the vnion of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches aboue all other Catholikes, vnder which pretenſed zeale, you now at laſt leaue the Church. Which pride of yours you diſcouer in your 9. page in theſe words: <hi>I euer cheriſhed in me</hi> (ſay you) <hi>from my firſt entrance into holy orders, a kind of innated deſire, I had to ſee the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all the Churches of Chriſt. I could neuer brooke this ſeparation of the Weſt from the Eaſt, in matters of faith, nor of the South from the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne parts. I was very anxious to vnderſtand the cauſe of ſo many and ſo great ſchiſmes, and to ſpie out, if there could be any way thought vpon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177851:8"/>to reduce all the Churches of Chriſt to the true an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient vnion. Yea I did burne with deſire to behould it, and I was vexed with inward grief for ſo many diſſentions, which ſtrangely tormented me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If you perceaue not the pride that lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in theſe your thoughts, I will ſtirre them vp further. I let that paſſe where you call the Grecian Schiſme, a Separation of the Weſt from the Eaſt, when rather you ſhould haue termed it the ſeparation of the Eaſt from the Weſt; for we left not the Grecians, but they departed from vs. We Latines are not the Church which departed, but that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which departure was made. What principle of faith euer was common with vs and the Grecians, which we haue forſaken? They after they had nine times in nine general Councels (peace &amp; vnion concluded) ſubſcribed to the Roman Supremacy, ſo often againe with the note of leuity reuolted. With no leſſe apparant falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood you call the Lutheran defection, a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the South from the North, as if the South (that is Rome &amp; Italy) had deuided it ſelfe from the North, abiding ſtill in the faith of their aunceſtours. It is not ſo: for what is more knowne then at ſuch time as <hi>Luther, Zuinglius,</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and the firſt Nouelliſtes beganne to preach, that the North was Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, and imbraced the Roman doctrine, which now they abhor? The <hi>Roman</hi> Church
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177851:8"/>made no diuiſion, but ſuffereth diurſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made againſt her The North falling away into new opinions, Rome ſtill remayned immoueable in the faith which before ſhe imbraced; nor did the hauen leaue the barke, but the barke the hauen. But againſt theſe your conceits, I proceed no further, becauſe perhaps they are not ſo much ſignes of ſecret Pride, wherwith you were then taynted, as of newer errours wherwith now you are blinded.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I come to your Pride. Was it not a part of paſſing great arrogancy, that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but newly, and ſcarcely yet admitted to holy Orders, would take vpon you to be the Iudge of the whole Church? That you would cite before your Tribunall, as guilty of Schiſme, as well the Latin Church, as the Greeke, no leſſe the Roman (whereof you were a member) then the Lutheran? <hi>I would</hi> (ſay you) <hi>faine haue knowne the cauſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, and Schiſmes of all Churches, and find out ſome meanes to bring them vnto the true, &amp; ancient vnity.</hi> A great piece of worke, <hi>Antony,</hi> and hardly to be diſpacht in a generall Councell of the Church; much leſſe are the ſhoulders of a puny Clergy man, as you were then, able to ſuſtaine the burthen thereof. But what neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity was it for you, to intrude your ſelfe into the ſearch of this cauſe? Generall Councells had already heard this controuerſie of ſchiſms,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177851:9"/>they had before hand conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned both Greeks and Lutherans;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyprian. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6.</note> they had concluded with Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, <hi>That Schiſmes, &amp; Hereſies do, and haue euer ſprunge vp from no other cauſe then this, that the Biſhop which is one, and gouernes the Church, by the proud preſumption of ſome, is ſet at naught; and the man by Gods ordinance honoured, by moſt vnworthy men is adiudged: nor that there is any other way of vnion, and of extinguiſhing hereſies, then that they returne to the fountaine of vnity, and imbrace that Catholike proofe, a ſhort an eaſie way of belief, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyning the Epitome of truth, which our Lord appoynted,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>when he ſpake to Peter: Thou art Peter, and vpon this Rock will I build my Church. That he that forſaketh Peters Chaire, whereupon the Church is founded, cannot be of the Church.</hi> This is the only cauſe of Schiſme, this the only way to vnity, this the definition of the Fathers, and of the Church. This, you being then a Ieſuite and a Clergy man, could not be ignorant of, nor doubt of being a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike (if you were ſo indeed;) why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did not this iudgment of the Church quiet you? Why did you <hi>vexe your ſelfe in the ſearch of another cauſe of Schiſmes, and another way of vnion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Certainly you then beganne to breed that which you haue now at laſt brought forth, or at leaſt you leaue the Church, to the end you may bring it forth, which is a certaine ſtrange,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177851:9"/>and wonderfull deuice to vnite all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in one, whereby all Chriſtian ſocietyes (although differing in Religion among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; from Peters Seate) are thruſt vp into one Body of a Church, without any vniuerſal Head or Prince to gouerne them. This is the ſpeciall new doctrine you come to preach, this the great ſuppoſed light, wherein you now exult, a glimps wherof Sathan transfiguring himſelfe into an Angell of light, long ago pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto you. And what was this elſe but to make your ſelfe wiſer then all Catholikes beſides? then Councells, Fathers, and the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church? yea which is more, wiſer then Chriſt himſelfe, who when he ſaw that the peace of his Church could not otherwiſe ſtand without a Gouernour,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leo ep.</hi> 84.</note> he made Peter the chiefe of his Apoſtles, <hi>That in fellow-ſhip of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, there might be a certaine difference of power:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hier. cont. Iouin.</note> 
                     <hi>and that by appointing a head, the occaſion of ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me might be vtterly taken away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. If (as you would make vs belieue) you had byn inflamed with the true zeale of ſoules, you would neuer haue ſo anxiouſly ſearched into new cauſes of ſchiſmes, but rather haue laboured to remoue thoſe which are now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſcouered by Fathers, and Councells, peſtering the world to the ruine of many. You would not haue byn ſo prodigall of your vaine and proud teares for the Chriſtian Churches,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177851:10"/>and for the Roman it ſelf with the reſt, whoſe child you were; but rather taking compaſſion of nations wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring from the Roman Church you would haue ſtudied to reduce them to the head-ſpring of vnity, by word, example, writing, labours, perills, and laſtly with your life laid downe in pawne for teſtimony ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. This had beene the part of a wiſe man, of one burning in Charity, of a Ieſuite. But whileſt your fellowes the Ieſuites, with other Preachers of the Faith, ſweat out their bloud for the vnion of Churches, and the vtter ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of ſchiſme, you, forſooth, burning with zeale, innated not infuſed, humane not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, at home in your idle and imaginary tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles, diſcouer new found wayes of conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſuch as were neuer trod on by any foote before. Thus you vaniſhed away in your owne cogitations: whilſt you toyled your ſelfe in ſeeking out new and vnuſed wayes, you loſt the auncient and ready way: whileſt in the Catholike way, with the foote of pride you ſtroue to go beyond the reſt, from the Catholike truth were you caſt away, &amp; could not ſtand.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond degree,</hi> Secret Infidelity.</head>
                  <p>FOR whiles you ſit in your throne vmpiere of Churches, you begin your ſelfe to ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177851:10"/>in the Catholike faith: that you might at laſt become an Apoſtata, it was needfull, that you ſhould firſt doubt of your faith, that ſo the ſaying of Hilary might ſtand for good.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hilar. l.</hi> 6. <hi>de Trin.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Well may hereſy tempt an vnperfect man, but it cannot ſupplant the perfect.</hi> Cyprian ſaith: <hi>Let no man thinke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cyprian. de vnit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. ca.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>that good men can departe from the Church; The wind blowes not away the Corne, nor doth the tempeſt ouerthrow the Tree that is well rooted in the ground; The ſlighter chaffe is carried away with the winde; the weaker trees by force of ſtormes are ouerthrowne. Theſe are thoſe whom the Apoſtle Iohn noteth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaying. They went out from vs, but they were not of vs: For had they beene of vs, they would no doubt haue ſtayed with vs.</hi> It is ſo indeed <hi>(Antony)</hi> you were none of ours, euen when you ſeemed moſt to be ours; you were euer of a doubtfull Faith, and of a wit propenſe to hereſy: This, thoſe that know you, teſtify; this you ſeeme not to deny of your ſelfe, and this will I demonſtrate with a double argument out of your owne ſpeaches.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Firſt in your eight page you write, <hi>that continually you felt temptations</hi> (which now you terme ſparckles of the inward ſpirit) <hi>about cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuppoſed doctrines of the Roman faith, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> (ſay you) <hi>I could neuer reſt ſatisfied, nor free my ſelfe wholy from a vehement ſuſpition, which euer held me perplexed, as I grew more aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in the ſtudies of ſacred diuinity.</hi> What thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177851:11"/>temptations were, and againſt what articles of the Roman faith, you ſet not downe: you leaue it to our choyce, to thinke that you all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways had a doubt of the myſteries of the moſt holy Trinity, of the Incarnation, and the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, with others; for theſe alſo are the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the proper Roman faith, which it conſtantly manteynes againſt the old here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, and many of the reformed (or deformed rather) of this vpſtart Ghoſpell. Nor can you ſay, that you ſignified your temptations only, but gaue no aſſent or conſent thereunto. For this is confuted out of that which you write in the ſame pag. 8. <hi>I haue truly alwaies thought it</hi> (ſay you) <hi>a matter not voyde of ſuſpition (as reaſon teacheth) that the bookes contrary to the Roman doctrine, ſhould be barred from the ſtudents, and from thoſe that are well affected to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith.</hi> You plainly confeſſe by this, that you had not only a motion of doubt againſt faith, but an aſſent alſo: nor were you tempted only, but you aſſented likewiſe to that which the temptation ſuggeſted, (to wit) that the Roman faith was, if not falſe, at leaſt wiſe not free from ſuſpition of falſhood.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. From hence is deriued the ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of your ſecret Infidelity. You ſay that you euer haue ſuſpected the Roman Church, becauſe ſhe layeth thoſe bookes out of ſight which are any waies contrary to her doctrine.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177851:11"/>And by and by you explicate more cleerely your ſuſpition (to wit:) <hi>That ſomething there was no doubt in the bookes of heretikes, which the Roman doctrine was not able to conuince.</hi> I take you at your word, that you alwaies ſuſpected the Proteſtants doctrine to be ſounder then the Catholikes. What may be deduced from this? Euen this, that you were neuer a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like indeed, neuer truly indued with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Faith. For he that beleeues like a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and a Chriſtian, this thing of all other firſt and chiefly he belieues, that nothing may be found ſurer or holier then his faith. And this perſuaſion if it be vnſteddy and wauering, is no Faith, nor the ſubſtance of thinges hoped for, nor the firme and immoueable ground of ſaluation.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertul. praeſc. ca.</hi> 8.</note> 
                     <hi>When we beleeue</hi> (ſaith Tertullian) <hi>we deſire to belieue no more, for this thing we firſt of all belieue, that there is not ought elſe to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> And againe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibidem c.</hi> 11</note> 
                     <hi>No man ſeekes for that which he hath not loſt, or neuer had. If you belieue the things that you ought to belieue, and yet imagine ſomething elſe to be ſought for, then ſurely you hope, that there is ſomething elſe to be found; which you would neuer do, but becauſe either you did not belieue that which you ſeemed to belieue, or elſe now you haue left to belieue. Thus leauing your Faith you are found a denyer.</hi> Thus Tertullian. Who ſeemes (Antony) to ſpeake to you, your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience he conuents: you ſay that, <hi>with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177851:12"/>you haue alwaies eſteemed the Roman doctrine to be touched with ſuſpition of infirmity.</hi> Is this you ſpeake, true or falſe? If falſe, who hath ſo bewitched you to giue the lye to your owne ſelfe? how is it likely that you will ſpeake well of the Pope whome you hate, that ſpare not your owne ſelfe? he that is not good to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to whome will he be good? If true, how were you euer a Catholike, and a Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, that haue alwaies iudged the Roman doctrine (if not openly falſe) yet lying open to ſuſpitions of falſhood, and no way ſecure?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Since then you confeſſe your Faith to haue been euer ſo ſickly and feeble, we trouble not our ſelues with the ſearching out of thoſe decrees and myſteries of the Roman Faith wherof you doubted: But in reward of your ingenuous confeſſion, we do of our owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord vouchſafe you the graunt of your ſuite, which you ſo painefully endeauour in this writing to obtayne of vs. For you deſire, <hi>that your departure may breed no admiration in vs;</hi> Your ſuite (Antony) is reaſonable, and not amiſſe for vs. For it is the part of a Chriſtian rather to eſchewe hereſies, whereof Chriſt foretold vs,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.19. <hi>Act</hi> 20.</note> then to wonder at them: not to wonder I ſay, though <hi>the ſtarres ſhould fall from heauen,</hi> or that, <hi>from among Biſhops whome Chriſt hath placed to gouerne his Church purchaſed by his bloud, there ſhould ariſe men lying, and ſpeaking
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177851:12"/>peruerſly: Wonderers</hi> (as Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith) by the fall of certaine perſons which were held for learned, or holy men, <hi>are edified to their owne deſtruction: They vnderſtand not that we ought to receaue Doctours with the Church, and not with Doctours forſake the Church, nor to eſteeme the Faith, for the perſons that imbrace it, but the perſons for the Faith they imbrace.</hi> But as for you (Antony) why ſhould we wonder at your fall, ſeeing you confeſſe, that you were neuer ſtable.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cypr. epiſt.</hi> 52. <hi>ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Graue men</hi> (ſaith S. Cyprian) <hi>and ſuch as are once well &amp; ſoundly founded on the rock, are not ſhaken with wind or ſtormes, much leſſe remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a ſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y blaſt.</hi> It were a wonder indeed if ſuch men ſo grounded in the faith ſhould fal: but you that neuer ſtood faſt vpon the Rock, <hi>againſt which the proud gats of hel cannot preuaile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. cont. part. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat.</note> you that alwaies had the ſayles of you high mind ſpread to the winds of nouelty, you that continually ſuſpected the infallible doctrines of the Roman Church for feeble, you being ſo doubtfull, and vncertaine; no meruayle if at laſt, toſſed with diuers fancies, as it were with certaine blaſtes of windes ruſhing vpon you, you were beaten from your firſt purpoſe. The Faith that in your ſelfe already was falſe, could not long retayne the ſemblance of ſtanding.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="degree">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:177851:13"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third degree,</hi> Suſpicious Lightnes, and Inconſtancy.</head>
                  <p>BVT now if we do looke into the cauſes of theſe your doubts, ſuch cauſes eſpecially which you commit to writing, ſtraight ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth your ſuſpicious Leuitie, readily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with euery blaſt. You obiect for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth errours, abuſes, and innumerable nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to the Roman Church, but they are but words only: For in particuler you do not ſo much as name them, much leſſe proue them. Namely and eſpecially you vrge two incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your change, two things that ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized you in the Catholike Church, which we will now examine, and lay open the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty you diſcouer therein. The firſt in your 8. page, you ſet downe in theſe words. <hi>That which made me more doubtfull, was the exact and rigorous diligence vſed both at Rome, and in my owne Countrey; Wherby a moſt vigilant heed is taken, that no books contrary to the Roman do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, be handled or read of any: good reaſon I thought there was, that the vulgar ſort ſhould be forbidden them: But that ſtudents, and thoſe very well affected to the Catholike faith, and well knowne to be ſound in doctrine, ſhould wholy be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of them, I haue euer thought it a matter of ſuſpition. And in hiding, ſuppreſsing, and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177851:13"/>of ſuch books, ſo much induſtry is had, that for this cauſe only a man may well ſuſpect, that there is ſomething in them, which our doctrine is not able to conuince.</hi> Two things you ſay; firſt that you haue always had the Roman Church in ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe ſhe prohibits the aduerſaries books. The other is, that for this very cauſe her doctrine may wel be called in queſtion By the firſt you bewray the inſtability of your mind, but in the ſecond your impiety alſo.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. For the firſt then, what a lightnes &amp; inconſtancy is it, vpon ſo vaine a ſuſpition to renounce the Church, eſpecially that Church that hath bred you to Chriſt? <hi>In whoſe lap</hi> (to vſe S. Auguſtins words) <hi>many iuſt reſpects ſhould haue held you:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. cont. Epiſt. run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. cup.</hi> 3.</note> (to witt) <hi>the conſent of people and notions, the authority which was firſt bred by miracles, nurſed by hope, brought vp by charity, founded in antiquity. The ſucceſsion of Prieſts, euen from the ſeate of Peter the Apoſtle, to whome our Lord after his reſurrection committed his flock, vnto this preſent Biſhoprick. Laſtly the name</hi> Catholike; <hi>which not without cauſe this Church only, amongſt ſo many hereſies, hitherto hath enioyed.</hi> But (ſay you) ſhe ſmothers, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, and deſtroyeth the aduerſaries books by all meanes poſſible: ſhe do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h ſo indeed; like a mother ſhe wiſely, and piouſly tenders the good of her children; like a ſhep-heard ſhe lookes carefully to her flocke; as the ſeruant of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177851:14"/>ſeruants, <hi>Whome our Lord hath placed ouer his family,</hi> forbiddeth them to taſt of poyſoned meates, warily preuenting, leaſt ſuch deadly food ſhould be brought into her houſe: what fault is there in all this? This is no diffidence, but prouidence, nor is the weaknes of her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is diuine, the cauſe of her feares, but the frailty and inconſtancy of mans mind: For experience ſufficiently approues (nor do you deny) that which S.
<note place="margin">Aug. cont. Epiſt. Fund.</note> Auguſtine affirmes: <hi>That there is no errour whatſoeuer, but may be ſo gloſſed, that it may eaſily ſteale in by a faire gate to the minds of the ignorant.</hi> And who ſees not, if dangerous Bookes for the vſe of the learned, ſhould be freely brought into Countries that are not tainted with hereſy, that ſcarce truly, or rather not ſcarcely can it be, but that they muſt light into the hands of the ruder ſort, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if they ſhould be permitted in ſuch a number, as you would haue (that is to ſay) <hi>to all Biſhops and Deuines,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 9.</note> 
                     <hi>that haue fully ended their ſtudies:</hi> Yea, and moreouer to Students and ſcholers alſo, to ſee whether their maiſters tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alleadge the teſtimonies of heretikes. This were too great a multitude, and would make poyſon ouer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon. Wherfore the Catholike Church with great wiſedome hath thought it more expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the learned, which may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely read ſuch books, rather ſhould want this vaine contentment of curioſity, or vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177851:14"/>furtherance of learning, then that the vnlearned, by ſo common bringing in of ſuch infectious merchandize, ſhould be brought into manifeſt daunger of their ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Neither truly as you ſuppoſe doth this daunger of drinking falſhood, by peruſall of hereticall books, belong to the common ſort of men only, whome you tearme voyd of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gment and diſcretion. I take it, you meane heardes-men, ſhepheards, craftes men, &amp; ſuch like: which kind of people, notwithſtanding for the moſt part is ſafeſt of all, of they be not more by others example and authority, then by their owne reading peruerted. The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger indeed threatens the vulgar ſort, but the vulgar ſort of the learned. In which number are found not a few raſh &amp; hoat ſpirits, men rather died then imbued with ſacred learning, that ſeeme to themſelues, and many times alſo to the people learned Catholikes, &amp; conſtant, when rather they are like vnto men eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouable from their faith, vnlearned, &amp; apre to worſhip their owne fancies as diuine ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Wherfore no Catholike vnles ſome giddy fellow, voyd both of experience and reaſon, will miſlike this Roman ſollicitude, in proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo carefully, that books condemned be not read raſhly and promiſcuouſly, euen of thoſe that are otherwiſe held learned, but with choyce, mature counſaile, and regard had to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177851:15"/>places, times, perſons, and cauſes. And if there be any, that would read theſe books, not out of an impious leuity to find out perhaps ſome better faith, nor out of daungerous curioſity, by ſuch reading to become more learned, but with a purpoſe to confute them; the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church will neuer deny them faculty, if charity be their motiue, and they thought meet for the burthen. What is there heer done but with great counſaile and wiſedome? What practiſe, that the Church vſed not in auncient times? Aboue 800. years ago more or leſſe the ſeauenth Oecumenicall Synode, the ſecond <hi>Nicene,</hi> Canon the ninth, decreed, that the bookes of the heretiks which they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, <hi>ſhould be conueyed to the Biſhop of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople his pallace, there to be laid vp amongst other hereticall bookes.</hi> You will ſay, that this Canon was directed only to the vulgar, not to the Deuines, &amp; to Biſhops much leſſe. Hear what followes. <hi>But if there be any, that conceale theſe bookes, be he Biſhop, or Prieſt, or Clergy man let him be depoſed: and if he be a lay man, or a Monke, let him be anathematized.</hi> What can be more manifeſt?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leo ep.</hi> 48.</note> But <hi>Leo</hi> the Pope for learning &amp; holines ſurnamed the Great, but much the greater by his office, with no leſſe carefulnes, <hi>ordeyneth, that with all Prieſtly diligence, care be had, that no bookes of heretikes differing from god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſincerity be had of any, yea and that ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177851:15"/>ſhould he conſumed by fire.</hi> Moreouer the fourth Councell of Carthage, or rather the fifth held in S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> time, permitted not hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes to be read; for Biſhops curioſities, but reſtrained them to their limites of time,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Can.</hi> 16.</note> &amp; neceſſity, Canon 16. ordeyning thus; <hi>Biſhops may read hereticall books according to the time, and neceſsity.</hi> Is not this practiſe then of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, both ancient, pious, and full of wiſedome? What will not the reprobate catch at to their owne deſtruction, that are offended with ſo holſome a cuſtome?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aelian. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> The ſpider ſuckes poyſon from flowers, the beetle being toucht with the breath of the pureſt Roſe dieth; yea that flower of flowers, by whoſe odour we breath life, to the Iewes was an odour of death to death. And you <hi>(Antony)</hi> are ſcandalized with the Churches piety in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing hereticall books; her prudence in this practiſe ſtrikes you blind; her motherly care you calumniate; you wreſt the motiues of loue to cauſes of bitter hatred.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Now as this other ſaying of yours, that the Roman Church for ſo ſeuerely prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting the books of heretiks, may wel &amp; iuſtly be called in queſtion for her doctrine; is not only in it ſelf falſe, but in the ſequele impious. For that which is ſaid of a thing, <hi>hoc ipſo, &amp; per ſe,</hi> that is, as belonging to the thing of it ſelf, &amp; by it ſelfe, is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likewiſe of euery ſuch thing,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177851:16"/>according to Philoſophy, nor any man, that knowes what he ſaieth will deny it. Therfore that which agreeth to the Roman Church of it ſelfe, and meerly for this reſpect, that ſhe proſecuteth her aduerſaries books, muſt agree likewiſe to euery Church, that with like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry ſuppreſſeth her aduerſaries bookes. If you do graunt but this once, then you muſt giue ſentence againſt the ancient Church, and reſtore to life all thoſe Heretikes, who with their bookes haue beene long ſince turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſhes. For we haue already declared, with what diligence our Forefathers, and ancient Councels haue prohibited their aduerſaries bookes: which care and ſolicitude Chriſtians, and pious Princes haue imitated by their Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes. <hi>Iustinian</hi> the Emperour, being in perſon at the fift generall Synod, by an Edict of his, which was read in the ſame Synode <hi>(actione prima)</hi> prohibited the writings of <hi>Seuerus</hi> an Heretike condemned by the Synod.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In</hi> 5. <hi>Syno. gen. act.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Let not</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the writings of</hi> Seuerus <hi>remaine with any Chriſtian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Et in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel. Const.</hi> 42.</note> 
                     <hi>but be had as prophane and odious by the Catholike Church, and let them which haue ſuch bookes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Habetur in</hi> 5. <hi>generali Synodo collat.</hi> 5.</note> 
                     <hi>burne them, vnles they will abide the perill thereof.</hi> With like ſeuerity <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and <hi>Valentinian</hi> Emperours (both firſt of their names) did proſecute Hereticall bookes in theſe words. <hi>Let no man preſume to reade, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, or write ſuch bookes, which withall diligence
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177851:16"/>are to be ſearched for, &amp; wherſoeuer they be found to be burned in the publicke view of all men: but thoſe that are diſcouered to haue kept ſuch bookes, let them be ſent to perpetuall baniſhment.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nicepho. l.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 15.</note> But of al others, the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great ſet forth the ſharpeſt Edict againſt the bookes of <hi>Arius,</hi> ſaying. <hi>Our will is, that if any writing of</hi> Arius <hi>be found, it be committed to the fire, that not only his wicked doctrine may periſh, but that alſo there may remaine no monument thereof: yea and moreouer we enact, If any man be detected to conceale any booke of his, and not to burne it forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that he be adiudged to die: For ſuch a one being found guilty of the crime, ſhal preſently be put to death.</hi> Behould how rigorous, how ſeuere was <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> What ſay you <hi>(Antony)</hi> to theſe decrees of Fathers and Princes? Will you now ſuſpect, that for as much as the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of <hi>Arius, Neſtorius, Eutiches,</hi> &amp; <hi>Seuerus,</hi> were ſo roughly intreated, that there muſt needs be ſomething in them, which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine could not conuince? Be not ſo blaſphemous I ſpeake in a word: If you know not the ſeuerity of the ancient Church in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibiting the bookes of heretiks, you are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: If you know it, and would ſuſpect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, that thoſe Heretiks arguments were ſtronger then the Catholiks, you are impious: If you moleſt the preſent Church ſtanding in equal termes with the ancient, you are vniuſt.</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:177851:17"/>
                  <p n="13">13. But now the other incitement of your ſuſpitions and doubtes is to be looked into, which then hapened when you firſt began, being a Biſhop, to turne the Fathers. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time you had not ſo much as ſaluted them a farre of. For thus you declare the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pag. 13. <hi>In the Theoriques I noted certaine ſayings of the Fathers, in many thinges very repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the common doctrine wherein I was tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp in the Schooles, and the ſame either paſſed ouer by my Maiſters, or not faithfully alleadged, or not ſufficiently, or elſe falſly explicated. Alſo the practiſe and forme of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, and ſpirituall gouerment of our times, came to be very different from the ancient, and thence my new mentioned ſuſpitions were not a little augmented.</hi> So you. But the holy Ghoſt ſaith truly of you and your fellowes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prouer.</hi> 13.</note> 
                     <hi>He that will part from his freind, ſeekes occaſions.</hi> For euery where, euen in your old manuſcriptes, did you hunt for ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, wherewith to charge the Church, which you had reſolued to forſake. And yet after all your diligence vſed, with ſo great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to find ſome ſhew of reaſon, the cauſes you haue found out be moſt ſlender, and ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as would haue moued no honeſt or pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent man to leaue a priuate friend, much leſſe the Catholike Church. <hi>You found the Fathers ſayinges in many thinges very different from the common Schoole learning, either paſſed ouer by your
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177851:17"/>Maiſters, or not faithfully cited, or falſly explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Firſt you ſay all theſe things, but neither are you able, or do you go about to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yet faine would you haue your departure allowed, euen by Catholikes. Shall your bare word be belieued againſt the Maiſters of the Church? Shall Catholikes themſelues againſt the Catholike Church giue credit to you a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitiue, an enemy? It were impudency to craue this at their hands, and folly to hope for it But admit all you obiect were true; how ſlieght is all you ſay; how ridiculous, and making no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all for the mittigation of the crime of your Apoſtaſy? <hi>Your Maiſters in the Schooles did explicate certaine places of the Fathers not ſo fully as they ſhould, or elſe vnproperly:</hi> you perhaps were by their negligence brought into great ſtraytes: were there not other men in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church learned inough, to reſolue your doubts, put caſe the Maiſter had not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied you? <hi>Sometime they did not faithfully al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge teſtimonies:</hi> how common and ordinary a thing is it for Scribes not to take well their Maiſters words which they dictate in Schools, though alſo what Maiſters deliuer in ſchooles be not ſo exact as writings that are prepared for the preſſe <hi>Some things he wholy left out.</hi> Surely a great fault. And are you ſo great a ſtraunger in ſchoole matters, that know not this, that the Maiſters cannot poſſibly in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177851:18"/>compaſſe of foure yeares, to which the courſe of Diuinity is ſtraytened, giue full and ample ſatisfaction to all the teſtimonies of Fathers, which are obiected againſt the Catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by diuers Sectes; of neceſſity many things are omitted which the Schollers after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward are to find out by their priuate induſtry. <hi>But there are certaine ſayings of Fathers which are very oppoſite to the doctrine, that now is cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the ſchooles.</hi> This ſpoken in ſo generall tearmes is true. What Catholike ſchoole man knowes it not? Who euer denied it? Nor do there want examples. The common conſent of Deuines is, that thoſe ſeauen days in which God accompliſhed the frame of the world, were true dayes indeed, diſtinguiſhed by the heauens reuolution, and the riſing and ſetting of the light: But who knows not, that S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> is of a contrary mind? The Schooles agree that the Angells were not created before the world; yet <hi>Nazianzen</hi> the great Light of Greece, eſteemes them elder then the world. I could alleadge many more, but to what end? How do they ſerue to cloke your Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy? Thoſe Fathers ſayings pretermitted, or not fully explicated by your Maiſters, did they patronize your Sect? You tell vs not what kind of Sect yours is: nor do you plainly ſay, that thoſe Fathers ſayings fauour you at all. Suppoſe you ſhould ſay they make for you;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177851:18"/>might we not iuſtly put you to your proofe? Laſtly ſuppoſing that were true which you ſay only, but prooue not, That the moderne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in many things now a dayes is different from the diſcipline of the Church of old, what makes this for you? Do you not ſee the times change, men with the times, with men cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes? It is the part of Eccleſiaſticall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ſuite their Lawes &amp; Statues with the circumſtances of times and perſons, to which purpoſe S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith very well: <hi>The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Councells are bettered by the later.</hi> Therfore <hi>(Antony)</hi> you bring nothing that ſound is, for you excuſe; what you bring are either bare words without proofe, or meere toyes &amp; fopperies, by which, ſeing you are moued to ſequeſter your ſelf fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Catholike Church, you ſhew your ſelfe more fleeting then a fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Get you hence therfore, ſince you will needs begon, and whileſt you are going we will ſhout after you with that ſaying of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian; Let them fly away, as faſt as they will,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tertull. praeſ. c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>chaffe as they are, of ſlender faith, blowne away with euery puffe of temptations, ſo much the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wil be the heape of corne, that ſhalbe ſtored vp in the floore of our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="degree">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:177851:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourth degree,</hi> the leauing of the Ieſuites Order.</head>
                  <p>THE three firſt degrees to Apoſtaſy were inward, and had fully ingorged you with ſecret Pride, Infidelity, and Raſhnes, which at laſt muſt needs be diſgorged forth. It was requiſite that you ſhould ſlide away by little and little; and that to this great worke of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſy from the Church, the bidding adieu to the Ieſuites Order ſhould be the Preface. The Barbar-Surgeon when he would draw a tooth, firſt with a little thred ties it faſt, then with often wagging, looſens it by the roote, and ſo draweth it forth: So doth the enemy of mans ſaluation, who being reſolued at length to fetch a man from the Catholike Faith, firſt in the very Catholike Church it ſelfe with frequent chaunges turnes him this way, and that way, and ſo ſlackneth him; nor euer doubts he to make him renounce the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligon, whome he hath brought to forſake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perfection. You write <hi>(Antony)</hi> that you were once a Ieſuite, and you ſeeme to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it; and yet you know, that he is not crowned that hath only begune, but he that perſeuers to the end. <hi>Pithagoras</hi> warnes vs not to meddle with Breames, which the <hi>Grecians</hi> tearme μελανοὺρους: why ſhould not we apply
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177851:19"/>this Prouerbe to the eſchewing of Apoſtata's, thoſe true μελανοὺροι, which denigrate and ſtaine their youth, religiouſly and vertuouſly trained vp, with a debauſhed old age,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iude. v.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>who hauing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne in ſpirit, conclude in the fleſh,</hi> and hauing giuen vp their names to Religious families, afterwards <hi>ſeuer themſelues like ſenſuall men, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd of ſpirit.</hi> In which number you are one, but would not be ſo thought.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. You tell vs, that the Ieſuites tooke your promotion in ill part, becauſe they had found you to be a very good labourer. You would haue it ſeeme to the world, that you forſooke not the Ieſuites, but paſſed from them do be a Biſhop. No man that knows the Ieſuites, will eaſily beleeue you. The Ieſuites inhibite moſt ſeuerely all ſuites of dignities, and if any be diſcouered to attempt any ſuch thing, he is forth with diſmiſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their order. They ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer leaue importuning the Pope by themſelues and their friends, to forbeare, if they chaunce to vnderſtand, that he do but conſult to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a Ieſuite. Nor do the Popes vſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance Ieſuites, vnles ſome great neceſſity of the Church do vrge it, or that the deſertes of the promoted towards the ſame be very great, that for the encouragment of others they may ſeeme, as it were, to be rewarded with ſuch dignities. What therefore ſhould moue the Pope, that contrary to the vowes, and againſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177851:20"/>the Rules of a moſt flouriſhing Order, and a thing ſo vnuſual, to create you being a leſuite, the Biſhop of <hi>Segnia?</hi> You may ſay the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Church of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gnia</hi> required it: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy increaſed, againſt which <hi>Hydra</hi> another <hi>Hercules</hi> was ſought for, the reſt of <hi>Italy</hi> could not affoard him: There muſt needs be a Ieſuit choſen, and of all the Ieſuites the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: In fine the lot fell vpon <hi>Marke Anto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y.</hi> Pardon vs, we beleeue you not. We neuer yet heard any thing that the dignity, or the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Church of <hi>Segnia</hi> ſhould be ſuch for which ſo great a Worthy as your ſelfe ſhould ſo extraordinarily be choſen to take the charge.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. But you will ſay, the Pope was indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your merits, not ſo much for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the Church, as for the honour that would redound to the ſame, by your being a Prelate: He would not haue ſuch a candle any longer lye hid vnder the Ieſuites buſhell: He would needs ſet it on the candleſticke, that it might giue light to the whole houſe. By the fame of your worthy name, you were grown ſo great, that the Ieſuites order ſpread through out the world could not hold you. The nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous company of men famous for vertue, and learning was inferiour to your Worth. But tell in vs (in good ſooth) with what ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of praiſes were you ſo conſpicuous aboue
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177851:20"/>the reſt of Ieſuites? Was it ſanctity? You may do well to tell vs your ſelfe the wonders of your owne vertues, who knowes them only. Perhaps for Witt? Bring forth ſome monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewith you haue adorned either Humane Literature, or Philoſophical Studies. The ſacred doctrine then? Amongſt ſo many Hereſies of our age, name me but one, which you haue oppreſſed with your writings, or which, whileſt you were a Ieſuite, you did though but lightly ſhake. In the Ieſuites Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of their Writers, ſo often by them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed with additions, you are no man, not ſo much as named amongſt thouſands. I ſee well, what you will ſay: That you haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed this name of yours, not by writing, but by preaching. For this among the reſt of your vertues, you account for one; That the Ieſuits would haue you ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preach in their Churchs. The Ieſuites (as I heare) in <hi>Italy,</hi> are wonte ſometimes to ſet vp weaker preachers in their Churches, that their others of note may take breath a while after their Lenten toyles, and that the people by a little diſcontinuance may returne againe to their better Preachers with more appetite. Happily the Ieſuites ſometims may haue made vſe of your help in this kind, (to witt) that by your tediouſnes, you might whet the peoples appetites for more learned Eccleſiaſtickes. I will not ſay it; but this I am
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177851:21"/>ſure, that if you ſpeake the truth of your ſelfe whileſt you were a Ieſuite, your were not ſo notable in preaching. For thus you write of your ſelfe now being a Biſhop, pag. 12. <hi>And becauſe now I acknowledged my proper Epiſcopall function in preaching, to furniſh my ſelfe with matter, I tooke into my hands the Sermonalls, and Quadrageſimalls, and as the faſhion is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to make vſe of them.</hi> Now who may not ſtraight perceaue by theſe wordes of yours, that you confeſſe your ſelfe to haue beene but a puny preacher, when you were firſt declared Biſhop. Had you been a well pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed and learned preacher, you would not haue beene forced to fly to <hi>Sermonalls,</hi> and ſuch triuiall helps, as beginners do vſe. And if now being a Biſhop, you ſtood in ſuch need of <hi>Sermonalls,</hi> and Lenten prouiſion of <hi>Quadrage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimalls</hi> for your preaching; a man may eaſily gheſſe how poore a thing you were whileſt you were yet a Ieſuite, at which time it ſeems you had not ſo much as turned ouer a Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. Nor can you ſay, that whileſt your were a Ieſuite, you helped your ſelfe in your Sermons by reading of the holy Fathers; for before your Biſhoprick you had not touched the holy Fathers, which appeares by that; that when your Sermonalls had bred a loathing in you: <hi>Omitting</hi> (ſay you) <hi>the troubled ſtreames, I who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolued with my ſelfe to repaire from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177851:21"/>to the fountaine of the holy Fathers, with which reading for my Sermons, I began to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much delighted.</hi> What is more cleare? At laſt being a Biſhop you applied your ſelfe to the holy Fathers, and by reading them beganne to make vſe of them for your Sermons. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing you were deſtitute of ſuch aydes, by which glory is wont to be purchaſed; how ſhould we once beleeue, that you before all other <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> ſhould be choſen a Prelate to honour the Church? If the Pope had thought good to ſet forth, and adorne his Church by a Ieſuite-Prelate, there was no want of moſt worthy men of that order, both for learning and holines. It had beene a diſhonour to haue made choyce of you, whome neither prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, nor writing, nor learning, nor opinion of ſanctity, nor any deſertes towards the Church had commended.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. There is no cauſe therfore, why you ſhould vaunt ſo much of your being a Ieſuite. The more eminent you were, being a Ieſuite, makes now your fall more ſhamefull. The corruption of the beſt (as the Philoſopher ſaith) is the worſt. That which is moſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the brighteſt light, is the vglieſt dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. That vice of all other is the moſt foule, that is the furtheſt remoued from the fayreſt of vertues. The ſowereſt vinegar was once the ſweeteſt and ſtrongeſt wine. Your example
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177851:22"/>confirmeth that which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth of his owne experience. <hi>That as he had neuer met with holier men then thoſe that perſeuere in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteries: ſo had he neuer tried any more wicked then thoſe that had fled from thence.</hi> The ſtones ſincke deeper into the mire, by how much higher the hills or ſteeples were from whence they tooke their leaue. Of this opinion was Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth, in whom the vertues of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great were reuiued in our age. Who as he loued the Ieſuites, ſo had he a true and perfect knowledge of them. He therefore when the Cardinall (whome they call the <hi>Datarie</hi>) had exhibited vnto him one that had been of the Ieſuites Order, that ſtood for an Eccleſiaſticall dignity, would haue the Cardinall conſult with the Generall of the Ieſuits, before he reſolued any thing in that buſines, and gaue concerning the Ieſuits this leſſon, worthy the great wiſedome, and experience which he had of ſuch affaires. As for the forſakers of the Ieſuites Order (ſaid he) let them be furniſhed with neceſſaries for meate, drinke, and apparell, for they for the moſt part are well brought vp, learned, and therfore may ſtand the Church in ſome ſteed, but in any caſe admit them not to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dignities; for it is not likely they would euer haue forſaken their Order, if they had not their wits ſomewhat crazed. Thus much
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177851:22"/>that moſt prudent Pope: which alſo may be confirmed by reaſon. For it is a token of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heate and vigour in a mans body to be able of it ſelfe to purge ill humours. And for no other thing more is the Ieſuites Order ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued of all, then for this, that you ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find amongſt them any man to faile in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and religion, that is not firſt by them diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarded from their Order. But as for you <hi>(An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony)</hi> how you behaued your ſelfe amongſt them, and how you gaue them the ſlip, though you hold your peace, the euent it ſelfe hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantly declared. You ſee therfore what a ſhame and reproach you haue procured to your ſelfe, euen by that wherein you vnwiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hunted for glory and eſtimation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fifth degree,</hi> Ambition of a Bishoprick.</head>
                  <p>AMBITION of dignitie followes next in the ladder of your downefull, <hi>A ſubtile miſchiefe, a ſecret poyſon, a lurking plague, The Crafteſ-man of deceipt, Hypocriſies Mother, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies Nurſe, the Spring of Vice, the fewell of guilt, the Canker of Vertues, the moath of ſanctity, the miſte of mens Mindes,</hi> as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bernard. in Pſal.</hi> 9.</note> The true mother indeed of all hereſies, which ſhe hath bred in the Chriſtian Church.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Euſeb. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates out of <hi>Hegiſippus,</hi> of one <hi>Thebulis,</hi> who
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177851:23"/>for that he receaued a repulſe in the ſuite of a certaine Biſhoprick, went about to ſtaine the Church (euer till then a Virgin) with note of errour. This reſtleſſe diſeaſe was the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt thing, that vexed, afflicted, &amp; ouerthrew you. For thus being oppreſſed with the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copall charge (ſo vnmeet as you were) you ſanke downe into the gulfe where you lye, and for euer we feare are like to lye. If you anſwere, you ſought not for a Biſhoprike. Cannot I diſproue you of falſhood by your owne booke? You do earneſtly endeauour indeed to diſſemble this ill beſeeming deſire of honour of yours; yet certaine ſprouts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of which eaſily bewray it vnwittingly, ſhoot from you. <hi>I was at laſt</hi> (ſay you) <hi>promoted to the gouernement of the Church, now abouc</hi> 20. <hi>yeares agoe, and made Biſhop of Segnia.</hi> What doth that ſignify <hi>(at laſt promoted)</hi> but only this, that I obteyned the thing I ſought for: <hi>(late)</hi> indeed, but yet <hi>(at laſt)</hi>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>—into my ginne</l>
                           <l>The wiſhed prey fell in.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> The word <hi>(at laſt)</hi> inſinuates as much, that the aduancement ſeemed long to you in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, which indeed could not come late, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in regard of your yeares, or merits. For you confeſſe, that when you were made Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, you were not 40. yeares of age, nor had then read the ſacred Scriptures, or handled
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177851:23"/>the holy Fathers. And how then were you <hi>(at laſt)</hi> and as you ſeeme to intimate <hi>(lately promoted?)</hi> Your wiſhes <hi>(Antony)</hi> made great haſt, ſo that the digniry which ſoone inough ouer tooke your firſt yeares that were capable of a Biſhopricke, but far outwent your merits, did ſeeme ſlow and tardy to your deſires that had rid poſting before. The hope that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred afflicteth: things deſired come they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo faſt, ſeeme ſlacke in comming, to the mind that burningly expects them.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. Beſides, you ſay (which maks much to diſcouer your ambition) <hi>That your Fathers, the Ieſuites, were much diſpleaſed with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</hi> The Ieſuites indeed are ſaid to take nothing more haynouſly in theirs, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Miters, euen thoſe wherwith the heads of theirs are adorned by compulſion, they rather eſteeme a load to their Order, then any wiſe a laude vnto them; but for the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſought &amp; ſuied for, they behould as a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſtayne. How vainly you wreſt the Ieſuits horrour of Ambition to your owne praiſe, as who would ſay, they ſorowed not ſo much for your behalf, as for their own loſſe, in that they ſhould be depriued of ſuch a labourer as you were, <hi>not idle, nor vnprofitable, but induſtrious:</hi> ſo do you proclaime of your ſelf: &amp; yet cannot I beleeue that you were a Ieſuite whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you were made a Biſhop, nor had the Ieſuites in <hi>Europe</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:177851:24"/>ſuch ſcarcity of labourers, who ſend often to the <hi>Indies</hi> men more worthy then your ſelfe. They were indeed grieued to ſee you hoyſed vp to Honour, whome they knew to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, prone to nouelties, and whome they feared, peraduenture, not like to proue very ſteddy in the Catholike faith. And perhaps with prudent fore-ſight they preſaged in their minds this great miſchief now falne vpon you, and ſo lamented to ſee you decked with the Miter, &amp; other Epiſcopal robes, like a victime adorned to the ſlaughter. Yea by ſo much the more their grief was increaſed, by how much they perceaued you more content and glad, euen then, when you moſt deſerued commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration. For what is more miſerable, then a miſerable man, who hath no commiſeration of himſelfe, but rather reioyceth vnder a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den impoſed vpon him, at which the Angells themſelues would tremble? Foule is your ſin <hi>(Antony)</hi> that being guilty of your continual and dayly increaſing ſuſpitions and doubtes againſt the Catholike faith, you would not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding affect Prelacy. You felt your mind more light then aſhes, and yet would not keep your ſelfe low to the ground, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne your ſelfe at home, but in the open ayre; on the top of a tower you expoſe your ſelfe to be toſſed with the windes. You intrude your ſelfe to feed a flocke, who ſtandes more in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177851:24"/>need of a feeder your ſelfe: you ſeeke to be a confirmer of others, who need one to ſupport your reeling ſelfe from falling: you tooke to your ſelfe the charge of ſheep redeemed by the bloud of Chriſt, &amp; yet wanted ſo much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage as to oppoſe your ſelfe for their ſafety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wolfe.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. Neither do I charge you with this cowardize out of my owne hard opinion of you, but you confeſſe it your ſelfe. <hi>Chriſt hath placed me</hi> (you ſay pag. 24.) <hi>as a dogge amidſt his flock: I muſt be mute no longer, as all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops vnder the Roman are mute.</hi> I preſſe you not with your raſhnes, where you ſo reſolutely paſſe your verdict againſt all the Biſhops of the Roman and Catholike Church, that they are dumbe men, that is, men knowing that themſelues and the Roman Biſhop erre, yet ſpeake not a word. It is an eaſy thing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade our ſelues, that others are as vicious as we are, <hi>and the foole</hi> (as the Wiſeman ſaith) <hi>walking along, thinks all men as himſelfe, and as fooliſh as he.</hi> Omitting therfore your raſh cenſure, I take hold of your plaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that you were once dumbe. <hi>I muſt</hi> (ſay you) <hi>be mute no longer:</hi> nay rather, you ſhould ueuer haue beene mute at all, eſpecially being a Biſhop, nor euer were you ſo without a haynous crime. Do you not remember that famous diſcourſe, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177851:25"/>ſpeaking to a Paſtour thus; <hi>You ſpied the wolfe approaching,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tract. in Ioan.</note> 
                     <hi>and held your peace: you are a hireling, you fled: you are guilty of the bloud of ſoules, that is, of the bloud of Chriſt.</hi> You haue ſtill ſinned againſt your erroneous conſcience: ſo longe as you haue beene Biſhop, ſo longe haue you beene dumbe. For you write <hi>pag.</hi> 12. <hi>That as ſoone as you were Biſhop, you perceaued by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our Sermonalls, how miſerably the people were deluded vnder the Roman Biſhop, and how the inuentions of Auarice, and Ambition were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced and thruſt vpon them for holy Decrees of Faith.</hi> Behould <hi>(Antony)</hi> from the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of your Biſhopricke, you ſaw (in your owne conceit) a huge wolfe, moſt pitifully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring the ſheep of Chriſt, yet were you dumbe for feare: you ſuffered them to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed &amp; woorryed. A grieuous wickednes. Now belike, being illuminated (as you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue) with greater light, you meane brauely to oppoſe your ſelfe againſt the wolfe, &amp; waſh a way the former blot of your daſtardy, with the effuſion of your bloud: nay rather you fly from your flock, and you fly as faſt as may be, yea and you fly to the vtmoſt corner of the world.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. You ſeeme to me like one of thoſe litle wayting dogges (their Miſtreſſes Iewells) who finding themſelues alone amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifes, do quake the while, are ſtill, or els for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177851:25"/>feare do whine and run away. But when they arriue once into the parlour, or their Ladies lappe, where they hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſafe inough, they turne againe proudly and barke fiercely: So do you hie you to the ſafeguard of the King of great <hi>Brittany,</hi> where you conſort your ſelfe not with maſtiffs that gard Chriſts flocke, but with thoſe women-wayting-doggs, thoſe wiued Biſhops, which are their Miſtreſſes darlings, <hi>from whence</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>you will bay against the Pope, ioyning your mouth with theirs. I aſcend</hi> (ſay you pag. 28.) <hi>into a place more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, where the Catholike truth indeed freely holds vp her head.</hi> So do you idly talke: but what ſhall become meane while of your flocke? <hi>A paſtour, and an Idoll?</hi> whileſt you are ſafe, and out of daunger your ſelfe, the wolfe (for ſo you perſwade your ſelfe) ruſheth into your Folde, raueneth, ſcattereth, deuoureth them quite either body or ſoule; what ſuccour from their Paſtour? I (ſay you) <hi>a little dogge, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the leaſt of all others,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 33.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall at leaſt</hi> (perhaps) <hi>with my cry, ſuch as it is, awaken the ſleepy maſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, which may chaſe away the wolfe.</hi> Nay rather why do you not girde your ſelfe for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate? Chriſt hath placed you as a dogge in his fold. What, doth he vſe to put ſuch barking Curres to guard his flocke, that do nothing els but barke, or rather maſtife dogges that can bite alſo? It is not lawfull for you that are
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177851:26"/>a Biſhop to be but a little barking Curre: For why ſhould you thruſt your ſelfe (being but ſuch a one) into the charge &amp; guard of Chriſts fold? Either take courage to encounter the wolfe, or deny your ſelfe to be a Shepheard? You will forſooth ſtirre vp others to looke to your flock, that may perhaps one day expell the wolfe, if not in the meane time, let it be ſpoiled for you. You at leaſt will ſleep in a whole skinne; and that you may the better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken the maſtifes, you will ruſtle with your Pamphlets (goodly ones in your owne iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) againſt the Pope, from ſome huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifes lap, whome you may chaunce to wed. I am aſhamed on your behalf <hi>(Antony)</hi> that euer there was ſuch a ſluggiſh Paſtour in the Church; but more may they be aſhamed, that ſo eagerly receaued you for ſome iolly and redoubty Prelate. Certaynly this raſh thruſting your ſelfe into ſo high a dignity, for which you were vnworthy, was the great beginning of your woes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſixt Degree,</hi> Contention for Prelacy.</head>
                  <p>NO man eaſily foreſees with what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes he ſhall entangle himſelfe, that once giues way to Ambition. Now then are you aduanced to be Archbiſhop, and with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177851:26"/>of your honour, is increaſed in you the thirſt of increaſing. To your Suffragans you ſeemed too great, to your ſelfe, becauſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Roman, you ſeemed no body.
<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> 
                     <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition is a fantaſticall thing; It cannot willingly abide any man before him, or yet behind him; It is ſick of a double malady; It enuieth the Superiour, and is maligned by the inferiour.</hi> With this two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Enuy <hi>(Antony)</hi> were you vexed; you wiſhed the Metropolitan Priuiledges ouer your Suffragans enlarged, but the rights of the Roman Biſhop ouer you abridged. Hence aroſe Spleene, Malice, Strife, with which whirlewind blowne away, you were carried headlong into Apoſtaſy. You would not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed haue gone but you could not ſtay, being once poſſeſſed with this paſſion; Euen as weighty things which caſt headlong downe, make no end of mouing till they lye on the ground. Theſe things meane we to make good: For that you write, <hi>pag.</hi> 14. <hi>I was lifted vp from my Biſhoprick to be an Archbiſhop, from whence ſprange to me a new, and more vrgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of renewing my endeauours, and of a more feruent and exact purſuite of them. For, when I began to be ſtirred with the moleſtations of the Suffragan Biſhops of my Prouince, but much more with the ouer much power of the Courte of Rome, diſturbing my Metropolitan rightes, I was forced to ſearch more narrowly into the roote and origen
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177851:27"/>of all the Eccleſiaſticall degrees, powers, functions, offices, dignityes, and eſpecially of the Popedome.</hi> So you. I cannot tell whether you wot what you ſay. For by this diſcourſe, truly, you haue wholy daſhed your owne cauſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated your writings of all credit againſt the Pope, which I truſt ſo to demonſtrate, that (perhaps) your ſelfe, or at leaſt euery man (beſides your ſelfe) may ſee it manifeſt.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. Your Suffragans I know not, nor haue I to do with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. You are their Primate, be you alſo Accuſer, Witnes, &amp; Iudge againſt them. They wrought your vexations: I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them not. They enuied your honour; they would haue diminiſhtit: T'was ill done. The Pope helped you not, but rather with his authority oppreſſed you more: See now how fauourable an aduerſary I am. I do not deny but that it may haue ſo happened. You grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at it; you tooke it hainouſly: You were incenſed and ſet on fire with anger. This I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low not, yet let it be held a pardonable fault, and, according to kind, to be ſenſible of iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. But you ſhould not fret your ſelfe ſo much, as to leaue the Church for the matter, ſo to boyle, as to ſeeth ouer the pot, not to skip (as the Prouerbe goes) from the frying pan, into the fire. If you will not learne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience of any Man, yet (me thinkes) you might of that worthie Matrone <hi>Paula Romana,</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:177851:27"/>no leſſe renowned for ſanctity then for No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of bloud. She (without her fault) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing incurred enuy, and being by S. <hi>Hierome</hi> exhorted to giue place to furie, anſwered:
<note place="margin">Hieron. in Epitaph. Paul.</note> You ſhould ſay well, if Sathan did not in all places moleſt the ſeruantes and hand-maydes of God, or if I could find my <hi>Bethleem</hi> in any other part of the world. Moſt wiſely, piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and aptely ſpoken to our purpoſe. Sathan is buſy euery where: That the leſſer do enuy the greater, that the weaker be oppreſſed by the mightier, is not Roman, but humane. If you thinke to eſchew this miſchiefe, you muſt wholy fly from men alſo, and not from <hi>Rome</hi> only: There are troubles euery where, iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, croſſes, euery where ſomething to ſuffer, but not euery where <hi>Bethleem:</hi> that <hi>Houſe of Bread</hi> is not elſe where to be found, but in the Catholike Church. The bread of heauenly doctrine, that doth ſatiate vs with Faith: The bread of the moſt ſacred Body, that feeds vs in the Sacrament: you ſhall find Bread in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the Miniſters Suppers, but profane bread, ſuch as thoſe which do take it, ſtick not to ſhare it to the dogges, whoſe crummes and cruſtes, without awe of religion, they ſhake of on the ground. Do you thinke this Holy Bread? I do not thinke you do, although to pleaſe his Maieſty of Great Brittanie you may feed of it with ſhew of much veneration;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177851:28"/>your anger therefore ſhould not haue lead you ſo farre, as to carry you from <hi>Bethleem.</hi> If there had been any ſuch iniuries offered you, either by the Suffragans, or the Pope, which you obiect, but proue not; they ſhould rather haue been for <hi>Bethleems</hi> ſake, togeather with that diuine bread, diſgeſted by you.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. But take heed now in the heat of your anger, and being ſo inraged againſt the Pope, that you vtter nothing for which you may after repent you. You ſay that the power of the Pope annoyed you much, and that he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted you, and your Titles alſo, and that from thence aroſe in you that ſeruent and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſire to ſearch out the roote and origen of the Papacie. Do you ſay this? You ſay it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly; your words be witneſſes therof: nor could you with any other words ſo much haue wrought the vtter ouerthrow of your owne cauſe. For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider I beſeech what you do. You moued with the wronges which (as you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelfe) the Pope hath done you, oppreſſed with his power, and for that cauſe now put into heat and diſtemper, ſet your ſelf to read, and write, and ſearch into the firſt beginnings of the Papacy. Firſt, who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that you will diſcloſe any truth in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Pope, if happely you find it, who burne with ſuch paſſion againſt him? That you will diſcouer (if you chance to light on)
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177851:28"/>the certaine and firme roote of the Popedome, the roote wherof to no other end you ſeeke but to haue it rooted out? That you will lay open the vttermoſt extent of the Roman Biſhops authority, which by a preiudicate opinion, you iudge ouer large now already before you know what it is? Secondly, can you hope to find out the Truth ſeeking it in anger, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo mighty a beame in your eye, as is the power of the Roman Biſhop, in the ſight of the enuier therof? Know you not the verſe (though vulgar, yet true)
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Anger doth ſo the mind bereaue,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That Truth it can no whit perceaue?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> Could none of theſe diuines ſayings occurre vnto you? <hi>Anger killeth the Fooliſh man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.2.</note> 
                     <hi>In your wrath you do looſe your ſoule.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 13.4.</note> 
                     <hi>An angry man rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſtrifes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iac.</hi> 1.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Anger of man worketh not the iuſtice of God?</hi> Could you not remember the precepts of the Apoſtle; <hi>Giue place to Anger,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19.</note> 
                     <hi>not reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging your ſelues.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31.</note> 
                     <hi>Baniſh from amongſt you all Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes and Anger, and Indignation, and Clamour,</hi> and laſtly <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> which is as it were a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fume of boyling Choller?</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Now therfore we ſhall not hereafter ſo much meruayle, though your ten promiſed Bookes <hi>Of the Eccleſiaſticall Common Wealth,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with Blaſphemous vntruths, which the furie of your breaſt, incenſed (as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your ſelfe) with ſuppoſed iniuries done
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177851:29"/>you by the Pope, hath powred forth. I ſhould wonder indeed if that were true, which you witnes of your ſelfe, in peruſing the Fathers in ſuch heate of your prouoked paſſions; <hi>That with your eyes more opened, you eaſily obſerued; you ſaw now, and throughly perceaued.</hi> It is a ſtrang thing that a man ſhould haue a beame in his eye, and not feele it; that being ſtarke blind, yet to himſelfe he ſhould ſeeme quick ſighted. But tell me <hi>(Antony)</hi> what ſaw you there in that your feruour and paſſion of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſay you) <hi>and throughly perceaued that at Rome, without all lawfull foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there were innumerable new articles of faith dayly coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and thruſt vpon vs.</hi> And do you not yet perceaue your ſelfe to be blind, that you ſee an vntruth; that you ſee that which hath no being at all; that you ſee a moſt huge nothing; that at <hi>Rome</hi> there are new articles of faith coyned, not in ech age, in ech yeare, or in ech day one, but euery day many without number, and yet vouchſafe you not to name vs one. But rightly S. <hi>Ambroſe: Anger waytes on Enuy, it fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtereth the mind,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Precat.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Miſſam.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>it dulles the ſenſes, it doubles the tongue, it dims the eyes, it diſquiets the whole body:</hi> eſpecially if the Anger be ſo impotent, as yours is, a gainſt the Pope, which moſt intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly you bewray in theſe words; <hi>The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty</hi> (ſay you) <hi>of our Roman Pope is not ſo great, that it ought to be feared: that temporall and ſtatly
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177851:29"/>Maieſty is merely counterfait, vſurpt it is, t'is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> So do you make ſhew to contemne the dignity you cannot reach to, rather then any man ſhould enioy it but your ſelf. You would haue it not to be at all, ſeing you cannot ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it with your deedes. You ſeeke to beate it into nothing by contemptuous ſpeach. This is the nature of Enuy, and the property of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged diſpleaſure. <hi>The Maieſtie of the Roman Pope affrights you nothing.</hi> So you profeſſe, yet S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> borne in the ſame <hi>Dalmatia</hi> with you, a farre more learned man, more holy, &amp; leſſe timorous of to yes and humane vanities then your ſelfe, was afraid of this maieſty. <hi>Your greatnes</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking to Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi>) <hi>dothterrify me, but your curteſie inuites me. Let the ambitious greatnes of the Roman dignity be laid a ſide, whileſt I ſpeake with the ſucceſſour of a Fiſher man.</hi> But it booteth not to ſtand refuting of ſayings which only malice venteth. That is now cleere which we intended to ſhew; That you haue wel trodden the ſteps of contention and enuy, which is the ſixt downefal of your ſoules haſty running into Apoſtaſy.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſeauenth Degree of Apoſtaſy,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy and Contempt of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Paſtour.</head>
                  <p>FROM the contumacy and contempt of the Pope, men do eaſily fal into hereſies, which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177851:30"/>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmes, <hi>do ſpring from no other head, then that one Prieſt in the Church for the time being, and one Iudge the Vicar of Chriſt for the time likewiſe being, is not regarded, nor is obeyed, according to diuine precept, by the whole fraternity.</hi> To you <hi>(Antony)</hi> as you were yet ſparkling flames of enuy, a fit occaſion was offered to paſſe to this degree, and make a nerer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vnto Apoſtaſy. For no ſooner was the knowne difference betweene the Pope and the <hi>Venetian</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth riſen, but ſtraight you bewrayed your ſecret, &amp; hardly concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led malice againſt the Pope by open contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. Thus do you lay the matter forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes in your 14. page. <hi>Shortly after came forth the Venetian Interdict; There was no end of Roman libells, oppreſsing, vexing, and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs Venetian Biſhops, as ſo many beaſtes, rude fellowes, men ignorant, of no conſcience. Hence new occaſions were offered me of new and more bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning endeauours, as well to make our defenſe, as to cleere the truth in the Venetian cauſe.</hi> So do you ſet forth the buſines, and togeather do lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the increaſe of your flames: you burned but too much before and were ouer hoate, yet you tell vs, that new fires and ardencyes ſeyze vpon you. You perchance affect the ſtile of Arch-heretike, and you would faine haue vs apply vnto you the ſentence of S. <hi>Ierome; No man can plot an hereſy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Oſe. c.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>that is not of a fiery witt.</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:177851:30"/>Such kind of Apoſtles doth moſt pleaſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent this vpſtart Ghoſpell of our age, which the Kinges Maieſty of Great <hi>Britany</hi> teſtifies in his <hi>Baſilicon Doron, to haue beene brought into Scotland in theſe later dayes by Preachers, that were of a fiery temper, and ſeditious fellowes.</hi> You delight belike, and would willingly be ſtill more and more enraged againſt the Romans, and that you may burne more hoatly, you fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne your ſelfe and your fellow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Biſhops to be reproachfully intreated, to be called beaſtes, rude, and ignorant, men of no conſcience. I haue read diuers of the Roman books written in the controuerſie of <hi>Venite</hi> for the Pope, but theſe diſgracefull and contumelious ſpeeches you charge them with, I could neuer find in thoſe books. But I may thinke that to the end you may heate your ſelfe the more againſt the Pope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you conceaue by imagination iniuries done you meerly deuiſed by your ſelf wherein you are like the Lion, who to whet himſelfe to the fight, laies loade on himſelfe with his owne taile.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. But ſeeing you deſire to be thought feruent, I will not contentiouſly deny, that you were more eager in the <hi>Venetian</hi> Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then any man els; &amp; that in your priuate contempt of the Pope you might exceed the publike. I make no doubt but to the flame, with which that moſt flouriſhing Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177851:31"/>wealth to their owne perdition, was ſet on fire, you added oyle and pitch by your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and Sermons to increaſe it, which yet was quenched by the Popes wiſedome, beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity and patience. His Fatherly piety preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ouer the Maieſty of his power. He choſe rather to yeald a litle to his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtoutneſſe, and to leaue the heate of their courage to be allayed with time, then to maſter their ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneſſe, &amp; pull downe their ſtomackes with violent or irreuocable puniſhment. The cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of this Peace liked not you very wel, whos deſires were now ſayling towards Rome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaging to the Republique, victories againſt the Pope. You with a falſe and deceiptfull hope, ſuch as Lunacy is wont to breed, had in your idle fancye (perhaps) ſet the Papall diademe on your owne head. But this compoſition did not only thruſt you out of your preſent hope, and imaginary Popedome, but for euer exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you as a diſcouered enemy, from Roman dignities. Wherfore the Republike being qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etted and friend with the Pope, the flames of your anger &amp; ambition alſo in outward ſhew were ſomewhat ſlaked, but inwardly they were no leſſe quicke and ardent then before. You intermitted not your earneſt and feruent endeauours, which you had taken in hand for defence of diſobedience; you ſtudied ſtill pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatly to find ſenten<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of Fathers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:177851:31"/>for your purpoſe. Ten years you ſpent in this paſſionate ſtudy, hoping the <hi>Venetians</hi> would againe breake with the Pope, which not ſucceding, a vehement terrour aſſailed you and made you haſten your reuolt: For now you began to feare, leaſt the league betweene the Pope and the <hi>Venetians</hi> dayly increaſing, you at laſt ſhould be turned ouer to the Pope to yeild him account for all your forepaſſed miſdemeanours. This feare gaue new fewell to your former fire, which now for theſe ten years had cloſely burned, and made it breake forth at laſt into the publike ſpectacle of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy. Let vs heare your ſelf declare the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of your ſtudying of the Fathers, whileſt blinded with paſſion you read them ten yeares togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>In theſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>I fully found out what I ſought for, &amp; much more then I ſought for.</hi> How wel you ſet downe the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of your fal? You hated Hereſie, but affected Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumacy againſt the Pope, and whileſt you will not leaue what you loued, you are falne into that which you abhorred. You would faine without loſſe of your religion haue remained an obſtinate and ſtubborne Catholike, but behould you haue made wracke of your faith, and are become a rebellious heretike. You ſought for Catholike contumacy &amp; contempt of the Pope, a thing not to be found; but in lieu therof you haue found heretical perfidiouſnes. Verily that haue
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177851:32"/>you found, which by ſuch an inquiry you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to find,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 9.</note> &amp; which al that haue ſought in this ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner haue found. <hi>For the beginning of Heretikes</hi> (ſaith S. Cyprian) <hi>is to take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in themſelues, with a ſwelling pride to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne their Superiours. Hereupon they ruſh into ſchiſmes, and prophane. Altars are reared vp out of the Church.</hi> Malignant feuers, neere neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to the Peſtilence (when the Plague is rife) alwayes turne to this miſchief, ſo neere of kinne vnto them; ſo when Hereſies abound, the Contempt of the ſupreme Paſtour (a ſin neerly allied to Hereſie) can ſcarcely be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined, but that at leaſt it will empty it ſelfe into Hereſie. Let them learne by your exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple that go about to be rebellious, what they are like to find at laſt. And let this be the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, That very orderly you deſcended on the ſteps of the ladder of Apoſtaſy which I ſet you in the beginning. You grow more ſinfull one day then other; you ſtill more and more fleet away from the Church, and euery ſtep you make, brings you neerer to Hell.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="degree">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eight Degree,</hi> Preſumption of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Iudgment againſt the Church.</head>
                  <p>THERE now remaines the eight and laſt degree, in the ladder of your deſcent, a degree and ſtep not only neighbouring vpon
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177851:32"/>hereſy, but alſo neere allied vnto it, which it doth not only touch immediatly, but is the very beginning and head thereof. This is too much preſuming of your owne learning and wit aboue the Church. S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>de vera Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. cap.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, <hi>That no errour can be in the Chriſtian religion, did not mans ſoule worſhip her ſelfe for God.</hi> For it were impoſſible that a Chriſtian ſhould be an Heretike, did he ſtill ſubmit himſelfe, and inthrall his vnderſtanding to God, and giue him leaue, by the voyce of his Church, to ouerſway their wits which are blind, raſhe, erroneous; not only when they wander without diuine Scriptures, through the works of Nature, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo when with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the boundes of ſacred Writ, they diſcourſe according to their owne fenſe &amp; arbitrement. Hitherto, before you openly fled from vs, were you fallen <hi>(Antony,)</hi> and being in that caſe you did not ſo much tend towards Apoſtaſy, but rather were you arriued at your iourneyes end. You cannot abide Subiection of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the obedience of Faith; euery where you impugne it, and at laſt conclude: <hi>I am no child now, whome being nigh threeſcore yeares of age, euery man ſhould perſwade what he liſteth without weight of reaſons.</hi> This your gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the Roman Church, contaynes either a groſſe calumniation, or a vaſt arrogancy. For if you meane to taxe the Roman Church,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177851:33"/>as though ſhe did vſe to propoſe to be beleeued of her children with true ſubmiſſion of their vnderſtanding, whatſoeuer a priuate man, or Doctour, or Prelate liſteth to teach; truly you hatefully charge her with that ſhe neuer doth: But if by <hi>whatſoeuer liſteth any man,</hi> you meane thoſe points of doctrine which you call <hi>proper decrees of the Roman Church,</hi> &amp; namely the Supremacy of <hi>Peter</hi> and his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, the doctrine that moſt of all offends you: If <hi>by euery one,</hi> you vnderſtand the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes &amp; authours vnto whoſe iudgment the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church would haue her childen ſubmit <hi>the</hi> (ſuppoſed) <hi>weight of their reaſons:</hi> If I ſay you meane this doctrine, and intend to ſhew your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt of the authorities that are by the Church alleadged for it, refuſing to ſubmit your iudgment to them; then are you come to this laſt ſtep, which conſumates an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata. For you know all Catholikes, all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops through out the world, and the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church now ſpread through <hi>Europe</hi> and the new found <hi>Indies</hi> acknowledge the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Supremacy. I will not preſſe you with the old Councells, I wil not vrge you with any thing that you may, or will deny. Only I ſay, that this doctrine was defined by the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Councell, by the <hi>Florentine,</hi> &amp; by the <hi>Lateran;</hi> which <hi>Lateran</hi> for the generall concourſe of all Chriſtendome, and for the number of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177851:33"/>that were in it, was the greateſt of all Chriſtian councells that haue beene hitherto aſſembled. Will you then ſubmit your iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the cenſure of theſe councells? You will not. The aſſembly of ſo many, ſo great, and ſo worthy men, by you is tearmed <hi>quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>,</hi> euery one, ordinary fellowes. Their iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts you accompt no more then <hi>quod quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> libuerit,</hi> you reckon them as trifles. Behould now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares the arrogancy of your ſpeach, which though you harboured in your mind, yet you ſought to cloake with ambiguous words.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. You ſay, that euery man ſhall not make you belieue what they liſt, being a man as you are of almoſt three ſcore yeares of age, you ſay that you haue reaſons of weight, that the Church ſhal giue you better, or as good before you will beleeue her. O craft of Hereſy! what doth not ſhe inuent to ſaue her ſelfe? ſhe ſees, that if the matter come to be tried by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ſhe will not be able to ſtand, nor ſhew her ſelfe in compariſon with the Catholike Church, that her vpſtart paucity will bluſh to appeare before the Catholike authority, which in former ages was, and now is ſpatiouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged ouer the world. What ſhift then doth Hereſy make? With full mouth ſhe cryes, that ſhe hath weighty reaſons on her ſide, hoping by the promiſe of reaſons to counterballance the Churches authority. If you will not credit
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177851:34"/>me that this is the tricke of hereſie, then heare S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 56.</note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> that long ago noted and diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this fraud. <hi>Heretiks</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>perceauing that they are vtterly ouerthrowne, if the authority of their Conuenticles be brought to compare with the Catholik authority, they endeauour by making ſhew &amp; promiſes of reaſon, in ſome ſort to ouercome the moſt graue and grounded authority of the Church. For this kind of boldnes is the common and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tricke almoſt of all Heretikes.</hi> So <hi>S. Auguſtine;</hi> which in truth toucheth your right, who go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to poiſe the weight of your reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt the authority of the Church. Nor do I capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly intend to wreſt your words to a ſenſe perhaps from your own meaning, as if before you will beleeue, you demaund of vs weighty reaſons, drawne out of Philoſophy &amp; naturall Knowledge. I deale not ſo hardly with you, for you meane (perhaps) reaſons grounded on Scriptures, but ſo, that except the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches reaſons do ſo fully conuince you, that it manifeſtly appeare to you, that ſhe propoſeth to our beliefe, that only which is conteined in the Scriptures: except you ſee this, I ſay, you will not yeild, nor do you thinke it meet that you ſhould yeild, being a man of ſuch yeares. Thus to ſtand vpon reaſons drawne from Scripture, is I ſay, an hereticall tricke. For thoſe ancient Heretikes, amongſt whome, as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, it was ordinarie to oppoſe their
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177851:34"/>reaſons and arguments to countermaund the definitions of the Church; theſe heretikes (I ſay) did not vrge reaſon without Scripture, but they boaſted that they had, and exacted likewiſe of the Church argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo cleere and ſo perſpicuous, that mans vnderſtanding cannot reſiſt againſt them. And the ſame kind of conuincing arguments our Nouelleſtes require of the Catholike Church; nor will they graunt any man to be an Heretike, but ſuch a oneas being conuinced by teſtimonies of Scriptures, cleerly ſeeth that to be affirmed in Scriptures which the Church would haue to be beleeued, notwithſtanding he refuſeth to belieue. This is their doctrine, which if we once admit to be currant, t'is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible there ſhould be any men in the world properlie Heretikes. For if that which the Church propoſeth to be belieued they find not cleerlie deliuered in Scripture, although they diſagree from the Church, they be not Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes as they ſay. And on the other ſide, if they ſee the doctrines of the Church to be cleerlie contained in Scripture, they cannot diſſent from them, vnles they belieue either that God can lie, or that the Scriptures of Chriſtians be not the word of God. And if they beleeue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe two things, they be not properly Heretiks. For if they beleeue that God can lie, they are not Heretikes but Atheiſts: if they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:177851:35"/>beleeue that God is true, but thinke that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Scriptures be not his word, they be not Heretikes, but Infidells; ſeing they wholy deny Scriptures, and, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>There can be no Heretike without Scriptures.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Praeſ. c.</hi> 39.</note> And if you ſay, they be Heretiks that deny the Scriptures, not wholy, but in part, then this followes, that there can be no Heretike which doth not refuſe ſome part of Canonicall Scriptures. And then I aske of Proteſtants how they can taxe vs Catholikes for Hereſy, who from the Canon exclude no booke which they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues admit; nor do we find the doctrines cleerlie deliuered in Scriptures which they ſo boldly, and clamorouſly contend to be contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in them. But my purpoſe is not at this time to ouerthrow this proud Tower of Hereſy, which is not to beleeue the Church, vnleſſe they ſee with their owne eys, that her doctrine is conteined in Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="30">30. This only I vrge, that you <hi>(Antony)</hi> were come to this laſt ſtep towards Apoſtaſy, which is not to yield to the Churches authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without ſhe make her word good by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaſons; &amp; that out of preſumption of your Wit and Learning, but eſpecially out of a great opinion of the <hi>ten Bookes</hi> you promiſe to print, you haue ſhamefully reuolted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church. That which we read of <hi>Agar, Sara's</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.</note> may very well be applied to you: <hi>Who
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177851:35"/>perceauing that ſhe had conceaued with child, ſet light by her Miſtreſſe.</hi> For as ſoone as you had conceaued in your braine that new forme &amp; plot of an Eccleſiaſticall gouernement, and Chriſtian vnion, you forthwith contemned the iudgment of the Roman Church, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhould haue beene obſequious, ſubmitting and captiuating your iudgment. But it ſeemes by your manner of proceeding, that you be of opinion, that in thoſe your ten Bookes, more is conteined, then in the whole Catholike world beſids. For you promiſe many great, &amp; wonderfull Benefits, which by your Reuolt from the Pope, ſhall redound to the Church, to witt, the ſuppreſſion of Schiſme, the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Churches, the extinguiſhing of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, the pacification of Princes from open Hoſtility, and the combining of their forces for the ſubuerſion of the Turke, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſement of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Captiues groaning vnder their yoke. Theſe are great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things. Let vs now ſee by what power you will performe them? As <hi>Dauid</hi> with fiue ſtones encountred <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſo you with the ſame number of bookes twice told will enter into combat with the aforenamed Monſters. <hi>The Church</hi> (ſay you) <hi>ſhall ſhortly heare my voyce: I will ſpeake to the hart of Ieruſalem, I will call her forth.</hi> Thus you, and yet (if I be not deceaued) God only is he, <hi>that ſpeakes to the hart;</hi> as for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177851:36"/>men euen the greateſt, the moſt learned, and eloquent, while they inuite men to heauenly matters, of themſelues can do no more but knocke at their eares. Nor do I ſee vpon what grounds you may be ſo ſure, that your voyce ſhould penetrate into the hart of the Church; though I ſee very well, that you imagine there is no ſmall force, but rather ſome diuine effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy in your voyce. Well, what is that you will proclayme, that ſhall be heard ouer Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome? Let vs now heare it from you own mouth. <hi>I will</hi> (ſay you) <hi>ſhortly put forth my ten Bookes of the Eccleſiaſticall Common wealth, in which principally I endeauour that the Roman Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours may be detected; the truth and ſoundnes both of Doctrine, and Diſcipline may appeare; that many of the Churches caſt forth and reiected by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, may be reteyned ſtill in a Catholike ſenſe; That the way of vnion betweene the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt may be demonſtrated, or at leaſt poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at with a nod, or finger; And that if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> (that is, if it be poſſible, my bookes wil do the deed) <hi>we may all ſay and thincke the ſame thinges, and ſo all Schiſmes may be repreſſed; that the occaſions may be taken away from Chriſtian Princes of oppreſsing one another; that therby the better they may direct their forces, in ſuch ſort that the Churches of Chriſt, groning vnder Infidel Tyrantes, may be recouered to their former liberty.</hi> Thus you write of your Booke. What victories
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177851:36"/>will this your Child yet in wombe get for the Church. What ouerthrowes, and woes will he worke vpon Heretiks, if he may be once happily borne into the world.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Whoſe birth therefore you iudge a matter of ſuch conſequence, that any wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may be committed, that he may be borne. For I pray you, is it not a wicked thing to forſake the Church? Yes certainly: and yet you finding no poſſibility to print your booke in a Catholike Country, rent your ſelf wholy from the Catholike Church, that ſo your ympe finding no other way of paſſage to life might worke himſelfe into the world, by renting his mother. Againe, is it not great wickednes for Paſtours to forſake their flock, to the continuall tuition whereof the law of God ſeuerely bindeth them? Without queſtion it is. Yet you write in this manner: <hi>It was very neceſſary for me to leaue my flocke, that ſo hauing broken alſo theſe bandes, being at more liberty, I might be the readier to praiſe the truth, and ſo much the ſafelier condole the ruines of the Church, which it ſuſteynes at the hands of the Roman.</hi> Marke, I beſeech you, your wordes. What is this els, but ſo ſay let the bands of the diuine Law be broken; let ſoules redeemed by the bloud of Chriſt periſh; all is well, ſo that I with my ten ſtringed Pſalter may get liberty to chaunt out the praiſes of Truth, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177851:37"/>the wretched ſtate of Schiſme. You hold belike the teares you ſpend for the Roman Church, at ſo high a rate, that the Bloud of ſoules, the Law of God muſt be ſet at naught and contemned for them. Yf you had ſuch a pleaſure to ſinge &amp; mourne, why would you be a paſtour? Why entred you not into ſome Religious family deuoted to the quire and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, and there haue giuen your ſelfe to ſonges and teares? Laſtly, what greater crime then to diſſemble in matters of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; with body to approach that Church whoſe faith in your hart you approue not? Is not this wickednes? Now tell me <hi>(Antony)</hi> haue you ſo ſoone vomited forth all thoſe Roman do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, wherewith you were once imbued? or haue you ſuddainly ſwallowed vp all the articles of the Engliſh Faith, that you haue ſo without guide of Conſcience imbraced their Communion? I cannot thinke it, but rather that you diſſemble in many points, to giue them ſatisfaction of whom you expect your hire, and to get the Kings Protection, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance for the priuiledge of your Booke, that what you could not publiſh in the light of Chriſtianity, you may at laſt ſet forth in the darckneſſe of Hereſie.</p>
                  <p n="32">32. It is reported of a certaine <hi>Zoilus</hi> that was wont to keep his bed like a ſick man, when (in truth) he was not ſo, that he might
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177851:37"/>thereby take occaſion to ſhew forth a purple Couerlet of his wherin he was much deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Such a kind of languour is it, wherein you languiſh, with deſire to publiſh your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; which that you might the better bring to paſſe, you feigne your ſelfe an Heretike in the Engliſh Church; you lay your ſelfe downe at the feet of the Kinges Supremacie ouer the Church, as though you were ſicke of that Parlamentarian Maladie; and all this to get leaue to print your Bookes, and ſhew them to the view of the world: and yet (alas) when theſe your ſo highly by you eſteemed treaſures of learning, ſhall haue paſſed the print, which by committing ſo many ſinnes you haue found out at laſt, there will not want diuers (I ſay not Catholiks, but Proteſtants) that hauing read your ſo much expected Booke, will apply to you that which was ſpoken to <hi>Zoilus.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Theſe riches are but vaine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Which make the ſickneſſe fayne.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q> I wiſh you would rather follow the counſaile that the Angell gaue vnto <hi>Agar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 16.</note> being great with Child, which was: <hi>Returne home to thy Miſtreſſe againe, and humble thy ſelfe vnder her handes.</hi> Returne (I ſay) home againe to the Church, which you haue forſaken. Caſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at her feet, your ſelfe, your wit, your learning, your bookes. Submit them to the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:177851:38"/>Catholike and Roman Cenſure. As <hi>Rachels</hi> ſeruant deliuered her children into her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe lap, ſo do you offer vp your Bookes to the pleaſure of the Church. But me thinkes I ſee you turne your head aſide at this, and ſay; This is baſe, this is ſeruile, this is to become againe a little child. It is ſo indeed: But oh noble baſenes and high humility, whereby a Chriſtian, tranſcending himſelfe and his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall wit comes to be vnited to God, reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling myſteries that ſurpaſſe mans capacity, by the mouth ſometimes euen of vnlearned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates! Oh happy ſeruitude that tieth &amp; makes men bondeſlaues of the Truth, which only affoardes true Liberty! Oh huge littlenes, which only art capable of heauen, which only canſt intertaine God! So that <hi>(Antony)</hi> though you be welnigh threeſcore yeares of age; <hi>you ſhall neuer enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, vnles you be conuerted, and become as a little child.</hi> They that ſcorne to be little ones, grow to be great ones indeed, not in wiſedome, but in malice and folly; which ſhalbe further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated in the ſecond part of this Suruey of your Apoſtaſy.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:177851:38"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF THE SVRVEY OF MARCVS ANTONIVS de Dominis, his Apoſtaſy. CONCERNING <hi>The ſtate wherein now he is.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE will not (there being no need) vſe circumlocutions, but plainly ſet downe the miſery of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate. By the former eight degrees not of beatitudes but of maledictions, you are falne into eight bottomles Gulfes, which within the compaſſe of Hereſy are contayned. I will firſt tell you what they are, and then ſhew that you lye plunged in them. Theſe they are: Forſaking of the Church of Chriſt: Not to be certaine of any religion: Hypocriſy: Mendaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the Church: Contumelious ſpeach: Arrogancie: Inuenting of new flattering do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: Vayne and idle talking. That you are ſwallowed into theſe pits belonging to Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177851:39"/>I will make playne, and by no other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then ſuch as your owne booke affoar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. This booke now pleadeth againſt you, but more dreadfull euidence will it giue in at the day of doome againſt your obſtinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance. Wherefore, <hi>Antony,</hi> riſe out of this mayne deep of Hereſy, wherein as yet you lye not ſo low, but repentance may reclayme you.</p>
               <div n="1" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The firſt Gulfe of Apoſtaſy,</hi> The forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Church of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>TO abandon the Church of Chriſt, and the Catholike Communion, is the firſt though not the ſhalloweſt gulfe of Hereticall peruerſity. <hi>All Heretikes</hi> (ſaith S. Hierome) <hi>are Apoſtata's,</hi> that is, Reuolters. The Apoſtle tearmeth the Heretike peruerſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 3:11.</note> becauſe no man is an Heretike that hath not auerted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſwarueth from the way of Truth wherein once he walked. He ſaith alſo, that the Heretike <hi>delinquit proprio iudicio condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that he is a delinquent, condemned by his owne iudgment. That you are in this Gulfe <hi>(Antony)</hi> is a thing ſo cleare, that it need not to be proued; yet ſeeing you deny it, I will proue it, not by common arguments, but ſuch as ſhall leaue you conuicted out of your owne words.</p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:177851:39"/>
                  <p n="2">2. He that forſaketh the Church of Chriſt and the communion of Saintes, is <hi>peruerſe, a delinquent, an Apoſtata.</hi> This you will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and that you do it, your ſelfe moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly affirme. For that you fly from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, that you depart out of it, in the pag. 34. you openly profeſſe. <hi>This my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting,</hi> ſay you, <hi>this my going out of Babylon, or flight, I will haue to be cleare from all ſuſpition of ſchiſme.</hi> You depart then out of the Roman Church which you ſtile Babilon; but the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, is the Church of Chriſt, the Society of Saintes; therfore you impiouſly go from it, impiouſly you call it Babylon. If you aske me, how I can proue the Roman Church to be the Church of Chriſt, the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Saintes: I anſwere euen by your owne words which are regiſtred in the 28. page. <hi>I may not</hi> (ſay you) <hi>be wanting in my charge, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Biſhop in the Church of Chriſt.</hi> And in the 38 page you name the Biſhops in the Roman communion, <hi>your moſt holy Colleages, or fellow Biſhops.</hi> When you writ this, you were in no Church but in the Roman, into no other Church or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany were you then by viſible &amp; externall profeſſion admitted. Wherfore you were Biſhop in no Church of Chriſt, but as you were Biſhop in the Church of Rome: or if you were Biſhop in ſome other Church, then were not our Catholike Biſhops your colleags
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177851:40"/>or fellowes. If then you were a <hi>Biſhop in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> and the Biſhops of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>were your follow-Biſhops moſt holy;</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes out of your owne confeſſion that the Church of Rome is the Church of Chriſt, the ſociety of Saintes. Which ſeing you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake, you cannot deny, but you forſake the company of Chriſt, and of his Saints, which is to be <hi>peruerſe,</hi> to be delinquent, and to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Praeſ. c.</hi> 8.</note> Well ſaith Tertullian; <hi>Erring is without fault where no delinquiſhing is: He wanders ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who by wandering forſaketh nothing.</hi> This is moſt true: but he that forſaketh the Church of Chriſt, he that abandoneth his Saintes, he leaueth ſomthing, yea a thing of great eſteem he leaueth, and ſo <hi>delinquiſheth;</hi> not without fault, yea with great impiety is ſuch wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring. And if alſo he leaue that companie whome he iudgeth, whom he tearmeth moſt holy, which is your caſe; then queſtionleſſe he is a <hi>delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent condemned by his owne iudgement.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Serm.</hi> 30.</note> Marke what S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> expounding theſe words of the Apoſtle, commenteth againſt your Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy. <hi>The Heretike condemneth himſelfe, who caſteth himſelfe out of the Church of Chriſt, and not being forced by any, of ſelfe accord departs from the companie of Saints. Well doth he declare what he deſerues at the hands of all, who by his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per doome, is ſeuered from the company of all. For whereas other criminous perſons by Biſhops cenſures
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177851:40"/>are driuen out of the Church; the heretike preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all, and becomes a forlorne from the Church by the choice of his owne will. The Heretike then doth ſuffer the like condemnation that Iudas did, being both delinquent and Iudge himſelfe, the authour and the puniſher of his owne miſdeed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. You will ſay, that you forſake the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church with body, not with hart, that you fly for feare of perſecution, but are moſt ready (ſo you may do it with your ſafety) to haue peace and communion with the Church of Rome. If you now pleade in this ſort, you will not be longe of ſo good a mind: neither can this anſwere conſort with your other deeds and doctrine. For in the 34. &amp; 35. page you write, <hi>that you are ready to communicate with any, that agree with you in the eſſentiall articles, and creeds of faith, yet ſo</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that we all likewiſe deteſt new articles, either openly contrary to the ſacred ſcripture, or els oppoſit to the aforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Creeds.</hi> Now I aske you, whether the Church of Rome teach new articles manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to holy Scripture, or no? If not, then you fly from her without any iuſt cauſe, ſhe being ſubiect to no cleere, or notorious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. If ſhe teach new articles that cleerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne with Scriptures, and will not deteſt them, yea ſeeing you ſay of her, <hi>that ſhe doth obtrude new articles that containe in them manifeſt falſity, and doth perſecute all that dare but mutter
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177851:41"/>againſt them, euen to the death,</hi> this ſuppoſed (I ſay) cleere it is that you haue carried away not only your body, but alſo your hart, your loue, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, and profeſſion from the Roman Church, which yet you grant to be the church of Chriſt, and the Company of Saints.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. You will ſay againe, that you indeed abandon the Roman Church, which is a Church of Chriſt, notwithſtanding you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake not the Church of Chriſt, but from one Church of Chriſt defiled with diuers errours you paſſe to another Church of Chriſt more pure and more ſincere, both for doctrine and diſcipline: but this deuiſe wil not ſerue to quit you of the crime of Apoſtaſy. For <hi>(Antony)</hi> the Churches to which you fly, be themſelues fugitiue and fleeting Churches, Companies which haue deuided themſelues from the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which had they not done, no Church, no Company had been now in the world, to haue receaued you in your flight. This do you your ſelfe in a manner inſinuate, when you call the Churches to which you depart, <hi>the Churches which Rome hath raiſed vp to be her aduerſaries.</hi> The time then was, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were not <hi>Romes aduerſaries,</hi> when they were not <hi>raiſed vp,</hi> but addicted to that which you call Romiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, lay proſtrate on the ground at the Popes feet. So that alſo theſe Churches haue abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Church of Chriſt and the Company
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:177851:41"/>of Saints, if the Roman Church be (as you graunt it to be) the Church of Chriſt and the Company of Saintes. Now then, did theſe fly to a Church more pure, then the Roman when they reuolted from her? No, but forſaking the Roman Church, they departed to themſelues being made purer then the Roman in their owne opinion, not by cleauing to the purity of ſome Church before extant in the world, but by the purity of a new Company rayſed vp, &amp; made more pure then any other, by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking and abandoning the reſt of the whole Chriſtian world. So Caluin ſayth: <hi>It is abſurd that we that haue departed from the whole world ſhould now fall out and quarell amongst our ſelues.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Caluin. ep.</hi> 107.</note> Your ſtrifes and contentions (M. Caluin) are in very truth abſurde and ridiculous, but much more abſurde is this your confeſſion that you made a ſeparation from the whole world beſids. For ſtraight out of <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, they that forſake the communion of the whole world, muſt needs be Apoſtata's. God forbid wil you ſay; for we haue iuſtly reuolted from the reſt of the world, we runne away from errours &amp; abuſes, we haue weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for what we do. No (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi>) you haue no iuſt reaſons, you are without doubt reuolting Apoſtata's,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 48.</note> 
                     <hi>for we are certaine</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>none could iuſtly ſeparate themſelues from the communion of the world;</hi> and againe.
<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>It
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177851:42"/>is no way poſsible, that any ſhould haue reaſon to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate their Communion, from the communion of the whole world, &amp; to call themſelues the Church, becauſe vpon iuſt reaſons they deuided themſelues from the ſociety of all nations.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> leauing you <hi>(Antony)</hi> no way to eſcape from the gulfe of Apoſtaſy, but by returning to the Roman Communion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>But</hi> (ſay you) <hi>I will haue this my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or flight to be free from all ſuſpition of ſchiſme.</hi> You ſpeake peremptorily like a Prince, <hi>You will;</hi> but you ſhould know you haue not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to ouerule the Natures of things. If you will take another mans goods without his leaue, and not be a theef; If you will vpon priuate reuenge bereaue a man of his life, and not be a murderer; If you will abandon the Church of Chriſt, and not be an Apoſtata, or Schiſmatike, verily you will miſſe of your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Theft ſhall be theft, murder murder, &amp; Schiſme ſchiſme, will you, nill you, <hi>Antony.</hi> Well, but <hi>I fly</hi> (ſay you) <hi>from errors, I fly from abuſes, I fly that I may not be partaker of her ſins, not haue part in her puniſhments.</hi> O how liuely did the holy Ghoſt deſcribe you long agoe. <hi>The wicked ſonne ſaith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 30 <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>as S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine readeth.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>that he is iuſt, yet doth he not waſh cleere his going out.</hi> You ſay the Church ſwarmeth with errours, is ful of abuſes, loaden with ſinnes, that you are pure, iuſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon fly, not to be partaker of the puniſhments
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177851:42"/>due to our ſinnes, who haue no ſinns forſooth of your owne to be puniſhed. You ſay <hi>you are iuſt,</hi> but you do not proue it; notwithſtanding though you ſhould in your owne cauſe ſay the very truth, yet could not you therby cleere your ſelfe from the crime of Schiſme; which I will make manifeſt, euen by your owne words. In the 37. page touching S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> you write in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. <hi>Cyprian made no doubt, but that</hi> Stephen <hi>the Roman Biſhop did erre very grieuouſly, yet rather then to make a Schiſme in the Church, he choſe to communicate not only with Pope</hi> Stephen, <hi>whoſe beliefe and practiſe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his, but alſo with others whome he iudged impure, for this cauſe only, becauſe Pope</hi> Stephe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>did admit them into his Communion: which example</hi> S. Auguſtine <hi>as he ſets it before the Donatiſts, ſo likewiſe he ſets it before vs for imitation.</hi> Now I will iudge you by your one euidence. For why do you not imitate this example, which you ſay is layd before you a purpoſe, that you ſhould imitate it? If <hi>S. Cyprian</hi> could not deuide himſelfe from Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> whome he moſt aſſuredly iudged to erre, without being guilty of the crime of Schiſme, may you reuolt from Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth vnder pretence that he errs, and not be a Schiſmaticke. If S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> had he forſaken Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> could not haue iuſtified his departure, by ſaying (put caſe he might truly haue ſayd ſo) I fly his errours, his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177851:43"/>abuſes, his ſinnes; do you thinke that your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Roman Church can be waſhed cleane from the note of Apoſtaſy, by your loud exclaiming, that you fly errour? A proteſtation vaine though it were true, and indeed falſe, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered without any proofe. You go about <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony,</hi> to waſh a bricke, you looſe your labour, your crime cannot be waſhed away without teares of repentance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſecond Gulfe,</hi> Wandring vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty about Religion.</head>
                  <p>THE ſecond Gulfe wherein you are drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I call Nullity of fayth, becauſe you abandoned the Roman Church and Faith, before you had made choice of any other Church or religion, that ſhould ſucceed in lieu thereof. You ſeemed at your departure from vs to be a blanke ready to preceaue any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or faith that ſhould be written therin ſo it were contrary to the Roman. A deepe pit of impiety which heretikes do fall into, whos property it is not to eſtabliſh, but to ouerthrow fayth, to beate downe Chriſtian Churches that ſtand, not to reare vp Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches amongſt Pagans. <hi>They ioyne friendſhip and communion indifferently with all Sectes</hi> (ſayth Tertullian) <hi>nor do they regard though they be different from them in opinion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Praeſe. cap.</hi> 40.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo they will concurre
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177851:43"/>with them to ouerthrow the truth.</hi> This want of ſound and ſolide faith you ſhew <hi>(Antony)</hi> by many ſignes and tokens. Firſt by your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſilence, not declaring either in the title or in the body of your booke to what ſect or Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you meane to paſſe from the Roman. In the title you pretend to ſhew the reaſons of your going, but you tell vs neither whence, nor whither you take your iourney. Motion (as Philoſophers ſay) receaues forme and ſhape of the end and marke wherein finally the ſame reſteth; which being true, your going, to which your title preſcribes not any end, nor reſtraynes within the compaſſe of any markes, what may it ſeeme, but a vaſt, vncertaine, blind, and inconſiderate wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? This your omitting to ſet down in your title the finall marke of your iourney, is the more blame-worthy, becauſe ſtraight in the very beginning of your diſcourſe you require that euen we Catholikes ſhould approue your departure. For how can any prudent man poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly approue your iourney, before he know in what Country, Church, or Religion you meane to take vp your reſt? We that know not for what place you are bound, can we know or approue your courſe? Seing then this circumſtance <hi>whither</hi> is the chiefe thing that giues light to them that are to iudge in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of a iourney, and therfore is the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177851:44"/>firſt thing to be declared in the very beginning of the deliberation, why did not you <hi>(Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny)</hi> expreſſe it in the Title of your Booke? why haue you not once thoughout your whole pamphlet tould it vs in playne and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect termes? The anſwere is eaſy: you tould it not, becauſe you were certaine neither of the Church nor of the Religion wherein you ſhould make your finall abode. You compare your ſelfe forſaking the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the great Patriarke <hi>Abraham,</hi> who following God, left his Countrey: which compariſon though in the mayne point it be very idle, yet heerein you are not vnlike to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that as he departed from his natiue ſoyle, not knowing whither he went, ſo you abandoned the Roman Church and Religion, before you could tell, what other Church or Religion you ſhould imbrace vpon the forſaking therof.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Secondly of this your doubtfullneſſe in choice of Religion, which you did but inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate in the title, you make open demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in your booke: in the 15. pa. wherof you write: <hi>Now myne eyes being more opened I might eaſely perceaue that the doctrines of the Churches, which being very many, Rome hath rayſed vp to be her aduerſaries, which Churches though we ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure &amp; our Deuines maynly impugne, do little or nothing at all ſwarue from the true primitiue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the pure Church.</hi> So you write, nor
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177851:44"/>could you haue more diſcloſed the vaſt pit of vncertainty in your breaſt, gaping for any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſo it be oppoſite to the Roman. For let vs ſearch into the matter. I demaund of you <hi>(Antony)</hi> whither are you going? to Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (ſay you) that ſwarue very little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the true Primitiue doctrine. I heare you. But ſhew me theſe Churches; which are they? they be thoſe Churchs which being very many <hi>Rome</hi> hath raiſed vp to be her aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? O what a deale of vncertainty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyeth couched togeather in theſe words? I let paſſe that vncertainty <hi>very little,</hi> which how much or little it is, no man knowes; you only may determine, and at your pleaſure ſtretch or contract it. I do not enquire where about in the world thoſe Churches are to be ſeen which you ſo highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend. Which que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould I propoſe, I could purſue you from country to country, and you would ſweat to find ſuch Churches in the world as you deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe in your booke, Churches I ſay for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber very many, in doctrine all oppoſite to the Roman, and all agreeing among themſelues in the pure primitiue truth. But pretermitting theſe queſtions, I only aske, when you ſay, that the Churches, which being very many <hi>Rome</hi> hath rayſed vp to be her aduerſaries, do very little ſwarue from the pure primitiue doctrine, whether you ſpeake of all the Churches and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177851:45"/>Companies that in doctine are oppoſite to the Roman, or of ſome of them only? You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not with truth ſpeake it of all, they being ſo many, and ſo repugnant, the one againſt the other, Grecians, Lutherans, Caluiniſtes, Libertines, Anabaptiſts, Arians, Trinitarians. How can it be, that they all ſhould very little or nothing diſagree from the true doctrine, whoſe doctrines diſagree mainly and allmoſt infinitly the one from the other?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. If you ſay, that though not all, yet ſome of the Churches aduerſaries to <hi>Rome,</hi> do very little diſagree from the primitiue truth, then I demaund, Why do you not diſtinguiſh theſe pure Churches from the other impure, before you prayſe them? Why do you thus at random raſhly (not to ſay impiouſly) caſt that great commendation <hi>to ſwarue very litle from the pure primitiue doctrine,</hi> vpon the confuſe multitude of ſects diſagreeing from the Roman Church, in which maſſe euen your ſelfe being iudge, all be not ſincere, yea many be corrupt, many impious, many moſt food &amp; ſottiſh? And yet by your words no man can perceaue whether this high prayſe be beſtowed by you on the Grecians, or on the Septentrionals, on the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, or on the Anabaptiſts, on the Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, or on the Arians. Verily you be not <hi>the mouth of God (Antony)</hi> you be not the preacher of Truth, who to good &amp; bad layd togeather
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177851:45"/>on an heape, giue your approbation without any diſtinction, not ſeuering <hi>pretious from vile,</hi> noxious from wholſome, hereticall from Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike, impious from Chriſtian doctrine. And yet herein you are excuſable. For what els could you do, who had not as yet made choice of any certaine Church you might ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnify before al other, being vncertaine for the preſent, and ignorant what finally your choice might be, you durſt not conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne any Church of the many oppoſite to Rome, fearing you ſhould perchance condemne that Church, which you might be forced to fly vnto. Had you ſingled one Church out of that number, extolling it only aboue all other, the reſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance would with leſſe willingneſſe haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained you, taking your ſingular prayſe of that one Church, as a diſparagement to them all; nor durſt you commend diſtinctlie and by name all the ſectes that are enemies to the Pope, knowing that thereby you might expoſe your ſelfe to iuſt exception that Catholikes might take at you, as being a friend of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble errours. Wherfore craftily you reſolued to ſhoot at randome in the praiſe of Churches that oppoſe themſelues to <hi>Rome,</hi> without ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying the name, or doctrine of any, that ſo you might haue both freedome to runne to what ſect you pleaſed, and ſhelter againſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, ſhould they except againſt you, as
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177851:46"/>fauouring the errours of any particuler hereſy. Now <hi>(Antony)</hi> perceaue you not, that your ſecret &amp; wily deuiſe is layd open? &amp; that this your booke brings to light the things which you moſt of al deſired ſhould haue byn hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Thirdly, ſo great is your vncertainty, that you are not only ignorant to what ſect to fly from the Roman Church, but alſo you know not, from what doctrine of the Roman Church you ſhould fly. I confeſſe you do par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularily miſlike the Primacy of the Roman Biſhop, but you were not ignorant, that the hatred of this authority is common to all ſorts of Heretikes. Whoſoeuer are wicked in the world, the more egregiouſly that they are wicked, the more mortally do they hate the power of the Pope, all being herein combined, Grecians, Proteſtants, Lutherans, Caluiniſts, Anabaptiſts, Arians, Turkes, Iews, Atheiſts. What other article of the Roman beleife do you condemne beſides this? You name no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but in generall you proclaime that you fly the Roman ſinnes errors, abuſes, and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable nouelties. Why name you them not? I will tel you: the ſects that band againſt Rome being very many, do not all miſlike the ſame doctrines in the Roman Church? What one condemneth, another prayſeth, what ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, others abhorre: ſo your religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on future euents you could not ſhew
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177851:46"/>deteſtation of the Roman errours in particuler till you had made certaine choice of your Church. You knew that you were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in the Roman Church, other articles did you become a Grecian, others did you fall to be a Lutheran, others did you turne Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, others did you cleaue to the Anabaptiſts, others ſhould you ſtay in Germany, others ſhould you fly to France, others ſhould you ſayle into Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Wherfore wauering in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties not able to forſee what ſhall becom of you, without naming any particulers, with all your might and mayne you cry out on the Roman Errours. When you ſhall haue made your election for your religion, &amp; therein ſet vp your reſt, then ſhal the Roman Church erre in thoſe poynts, and as damnably as it pleaſe that company you liue with to haue you ſay.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. But I pretermitt (ſay you in the 17. page) <hi>to ſet downe particularly the Errours of Rome, becauſe in my booke of the Eccleſiaſticall Common wealth I do fully proſecute them, which booke now a good while ready for the print I haue, and will ſet it forth out of hand, and bequeath it to the firſt printer in Germany, that by the way I ſhal find for the purpoſe.</hi> I beſeech you, <hi>Antony,</hi> why did you not performe what here ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemly you promiſe? Met you with no Printer in Germany that was for the purpoſe? or did the King of great Britany countermand your
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177851:47"/>purpoſe? or did you of your ſelf ſhrinke from your purpoſe? I ſearch not into this ſecret. This I ſay, that now you ſhall not print the booke you brought out of <hi>Italy</hi> with you, but another. Your ſelfe growing daily worſe and worſe, will change therein diuers things, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taking away ſome points of Catholike doctrine, or adding ſome new doctrines got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by your reading in the books of heretikes, to ſay nothing of the things which Miniſters by their arguments will winne you to alter. And what ſhall I ſay of his gracious Maieſty, ſo excellent for his knowledge? To change ſome things in your booke, and to adde other things to it, he will perſuade you by his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; to leaue out diuers doctrins that ſauour to much of Rome, he may compell you by his authority: percha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce alſo ſundry of his ſayings, though he vrge you not, yet you to pleaſe him, will put them into your booke. Know you not what befell <hi>Caſaub one?</hi> How much chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged he was from that affection and mind, that he ſeemed to carry with him into England: which alteration he going about to excuſe to his friend, plainly confeſſeth, that by entrance into the Engliſh Court, he was become a ſlaue, not daring in any thing gayneſay the Kings pleaſure; which baſenes notwithſtanding I am perſuaded did proceed not from the Kings diſpoſition, but from <hi>Caſaubons</hi> daſtardy.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:177851:47"/>
                  <p n="10">10. And as for the changes which I do now aforehand auouch wil be in your booke, we haue a fayre preſage, or rather a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them in this Pamphlet, which reprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in England differs ſomewhat from that you ſet forth at Venice. For in your edition of Venice, declaring the argument of the ninth booke of the ten you promiſe, you ſay that you largely ſhew <hi>quàm parca eſſe debeat Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrorum Eccleſiae ſuſtentatio:</hi> How ſcarſe the maintenance of the miniſters of the Church ought to be. The word <hi>ſcarſe maintenance</hi> ſounded harſhly in the eares of Engliſh mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Peraduenture when you wrote at Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, you prouided maintenance for Biſhops only, not alſo for their wiues and children. Wherefore in the <hi>London</hi> edition the matter is ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, &amp; you ſay, that you declare <hi>qualis eſſe debeat miniſtrorum Eccleſiae ſuſtentatio:</hi> What kind of maintenance Church-miniſters ought to haue. And when your bookes come forth, you may happily, to gaine the good will of Miniſters wiues, change their <hi>ſcarſe mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> into plentifull. You may ſee that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe you bragge that you will publiſh a booke brought with you from <hi>Italy,</hi> contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Roman errours, togeather with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cleere ſights and viſions of truth you had at Venice, and diuers doctrines different from the Roman, which you learned by the only
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177851:48"/>reading of the Fathers. For the booke you now publiſh <hi>(Antony)</hi> is not that you wrote at Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, it is not I ſay that worthy worke which you (as you vaunt) placed in the mideſt of the darkeneſſe of Popery, not hauing the candle of any hereticall booke ſhining before you, writ only by the light, which diuine illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions falling downe from heauen, yeilded to your pen; theſe diſcourſes of yours ſo noble and diuine be now loſt, vaniſhed away, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Not ſo (me thinks I heare you ſay) for though ſome points of doctrine may be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in my Booke, yet many, and very many will remaine. Suppoſe this be true, who will be able to diſcerne the reliques of the pure ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, from ſo many the new corruptions therof? or diſtinguiſh the parts of your booke vntoucht from the parts changed? your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient opinions from your new? your Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian beliefe from your Engliſh? his Maieſties conceyts from thoſe that be properly yours? yours which you lately got by peruſing the workes of heretikes, from thoſe whereof you boaſt, as if you had receaued them immediatly from heauen? No man certainly, though he be neuer ſo ſharpe-ſighted.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Fourthly, you bewray your vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in that to free your ſelfe from ſuſpition, and to meet with theſe inconueniences, you haue not in this your writing, ſet downe any
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177851:48"/>confeſſion of the faith you brought from Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; which thing was moſt expected, and it did greatly behooue you to haue done it. For this is the firſt thing which perſons reclaymed from hereſy haue care to do, that ſeeing they now openly forſake the Religion which once they followed, the world may take notice of the Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which in lieu therof they imbrace, leaſt otherwiſe they ſhould thinke them plaine Infidels, vtterly without any certaine religion. Wherfore you ſhould ſtraight in the beginning of your reuolte, haue made a plaine profeſſion of your faith, ſet down diſtinctly the doctrines of the Roman Church which you diſliked, &amp; alſo what you approued in the pretendedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches: for when you ſay of them; that they ſwarue from the pure doctrine <hi>very little,</hi> you ſeeme to inſinuate, that none of them do fully and abſolutly content you. This you did not; but ſeruing the time rather then the truth, and (as S. <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de Trinit.</hi>
                     </note> Heretiks vſe to do) <hi>being ready to frame your doctrine to the humours of men,</hi> by this negligence you haue changed the ten yeares of your cleere light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to darkeneſſe eternal Neither ſhall any mortal man euer know, what was the faith that ran away with you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Venice, nor what doctrine of Popery made you runne away; your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings will be not only charged with falſhood; but alſo ſuſpected of fiction, that you write to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177851:49"/>pleaſe others, what you beleeue not your ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Nor may you ſay, that in this Booke you haue made confeſſion of your faith in the 29. page therof, where you write. <hi>I am ready to communicate with all, ſo long as we agree in the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall articles of our faith, and the creedes of the ancient Church; yet ſo, if alſo we togeather deteſt new articles either openly contrary to the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or elſe repugnant with the aforſayd Creedes.</hi> This confeſſion of faith is too wandring and wild, within which all Hereſies may range, or at leaſt very few are excluded by it. And yet you are not conſtant in this profeſſion. For pag. 9 you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund the Roman Church <hi>to reſtore communion to all the Chriſtian Churches that profeſſe Chriſt by the eſſentiall Creeds of faith.</hi> Where you do not mention what heere you ſo expreſſely require, the <hi>deteſtation of new articles that are openly contrary to Scriptures.</hi> Moreouer how vncertaine and ambiguous is that phraſe <hi>openly repugnant with Scripture?</hi> For many kindes there be of errours openly contrarie to Scripture, and euen Proteſtants themſelues do mainly diſagree, nor can they define which of theſe errours muſt needs be deteſted vnder paine of expulſion from the Church. Againe you ſay nothing of the Iudge, to whoſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it belonges to decree which errours be new and clearly repugnant with Scripture. For if you require of men, that they deteſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:177851:49"/>thoſe errours and articles which to themſelues ſeeme clearly repugnant with Scripture, there is not any Sectary that will not do it. If you will haue all men reiect ſuch errours and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles which in your iudgment be new, and do manifeſtly contradict the Scripture; you do them wronge. For who made you their iudge? If you will haue the Controuerſy decided nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by your iudgment, nor by theirs; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the finall deciſion of a third Iudge, why do you not name him? Finally you do not declare what you meane, by eſſentiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, nor how many they be in number, nor whether all the articles of the ancient Creedes be eſſentiall, nor what you meane by Creedes eſſentiall, that being a new phraſe with I do not remember to haue read in any Authour Catholike or Proteſtant; yea the word may without much adoe be drawne to ſuch a ſenſe as no Hereſy will reiect any ancient Creed, ſo farre forth as it is eſſentiall. And why do you not rather exact full and abſolute profeſſion of all ancient Creedes, but ſtill with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of <hi>the Creedes eſſentiall?</hi> verily ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lurkes in this phraſe,
<note place="margin">In libro de Synod. Nican. decret.</note> which we as yet vnderſtand not: nor without cauſe did S. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius <hi>warne vs to ſuſpect all the wordes and phraſes of Heretikes.</hi> Why ſpeake you not plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ingenuouſly? Why dally you with doubtful and ambiguous words in the buſines
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177851:50"/>of Religion? but only becauſe not being reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of what faith you would be, you meane to frame ſuch a profeſſion of faith, as might ſute with diuers occaſions &amp; times, with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry countries and ſectes. Wherein you do no new thing which your anceſtors did not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in S. <hi>Hieromes</hi> dayes. They do (ſaith he) ſo temper their words, they range them in ſuch order, they ſo mince the matter with a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>biguous ſpeach, that they make a confeſſion both of our doctrine, and of our aduerſaries doctrine, that in one ſenſe taken their profeſſion is He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, taken in another Catholike. Neither hath this our age been without ſuch kind of <hi>Prothei,</hi> and Changelings, nor without theſe Camelion-like confeſſions of faith, which change their colour and ſenſe according to time and place. Such was the confeſſion of <hi>Ausburge,</hi> which to <hi>Charles</hi> the fift Emperour, the firſt Fathers of your Ghoſpell preſented. The articles of which confeſſion <hi>Philip Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> the Authour therof,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoſpin. concordia diſcord. in an. Domi</hi> 1527.</note> did of ſet purpoſe and ſtudiouſly cloth with doubtfull wordes. The reaſon of which his deed, writing to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> he yields, ſaying, that thoſe articles were <hi>now and then to be changed, and made to ſute with occaſions.</hi> So it is: your faiths be variable and monthly, <hi>but the verity of our Lord laſteth for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="gulf">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:177851:50"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The third Gulfe,</hi> Hypocriſy.</head>
                  <p>THE third Gulfe of Heretical naughtines is Hypocriſy. Heretikes (ſaith S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de ciuit. c.</hi> 8.</note> 
                     <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) be crafty people, endued not with the ſpirit of wiſedome, but with the ſpirit of wily deceit, wherewith their harts are accuſtomed to boyle, and ſo trouble the quiet of Saintes. And S. <hi>Hilary.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Trinitate.</hi>
                     </note> Vpon defection from the faith (ſaith he) wayteth lying Hypocriſy, ſo that they keep the ſhew of godlines in their words, the truth wherof they haue caſt out of their conſcience. But it is not eaſy within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the skinne of one Lambe, ſo to ſhut vp a whole wolfe, that no part of him be ſeen. You fayne Piety <hi>(Antony,)</hi> but you diſſemble in ſuch ſort, that by your owne wordes you may be detected to be counterfaire, which I will make euident with fiue examples. Firſt in the ſecond page you take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a pure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience. <hi>Our glory</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity of hart, &amp; in the ſyncerity of God, not in carnall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but in the grace of God I haue changed place.</hi> Thus you appeale from the Iudgement of the Church to the Chancery of your ſecret Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: you turne your ſelfe from publick knowledge, to your owne priuity, that is,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Confeſſ. lib.</hi> 10.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> from truth to falſhood. Shall I
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:177851:51"/>proue that you went away moued by the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſh, out of care to ſleep in a whole skinne, ouer which you feared ſome puniſhment was imminent? that had not this feare giuen you winges to fly away, you might haue been ſtill a Papiſt at this day in outward ſhew, and haue adored thoſe thinges which you now tearme Idolls? In the 23. page. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt me</hi> (ſay you) <hi>was conceyued and harboured in their hartes at Rome, who now had ſmelt out my labours in writing againſt her opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for more then once by the Nuntius Apoſtolicus abiding in Venice, was I warned hereof &amp; rebuked. Therfore it was my beſt courſe to take the winges of the Done, and fly into the wilderneſſe.</hi> Behold how clearly you confeſſe that feare gaue you the winges wherewith you were carried away from vs; feare, I ſay, not of the Romiſh Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, not feare to offend God, or to fall into Hell, but feare to feele the ſharpenes of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſeuerity; feare leſt the Republike would deliuer you vp, or permit you to be taken and puniſhed according to your deſertes by the Inquiſition.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Secondly, you make ſhew of great loue of croſſes, and of deſire to ſuffer for Chriſt, apparelling your affections in the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> burning with diuine charity. <hi>For my ſelfe, with</hi> Paul <hi>I ſay, it is a very ſmall thing for me to be iudged of men: let me be a foole for Chriſt, let me be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:177851:51"/>ignoble, let me be buffeted and curſed, let me en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure perſecutions, let me be blaſphemed, let me be made the ſcum of the world, an outcaſt, and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema, ſo only that I make ſatisfaction to Chriſt.</hi> Thus you ſpeake, and forward you goe with the words of the Apoſtle, ſeeming to long to ſuffer diſgraces and torments for Chriſt. But all is faygned: for if perſecution be your deſire, why runne you to a Countrey where you may rather perſecute others, then endure perſecution your ſelfe? Where you may ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely rayle on the Pope, blaſpheme him, curſe him to the pit of hel, as the outcaſt of the world and Anathema? The motiue of this your run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning away you ſet downe in the 23. pag. <hi>What ſhould I</hi> (ſay you) <hi>haue tarried longer in the midſt of a peruerſe and crooked Nation? If I would haue taught and exerciſed the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike doctrine, I had haſtened and brought vpon my head the moſt terrible Roman ſtormes, and moſt foule tempeſts.</hi> And is it ſo great a miſery tody for Chriſt (Antony?) doth death endured for the true Catholike doctrine ſeeme foule and hatefull in your eye, it being honorable and pretious in the ſight of God? for the Pilot being in a ſtorme to abandon his ſhip, is foule and ſhamefull; but for him to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter with the tempeſt, to venture life for ſhip and paſſengers is glorious. You deſire to be a Pilot, you will needs gouerne the ſhip of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:177851:52"/>the Church, but to be in ſtormes and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, to liue in perill of your life you cannot endure. Verilie you diſſemble <hi>(Antony)</hi> when you make ſhew of deſire to ſuffer, and little do you feele the affections of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe wordes breathing forth a burning deſire of Martyrdome, you borrow for your ſelf, which be no more fit for your deſire, then is <hi>Hercules</hi> ſhoo for a Childes foote.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. Thirdly, you make great demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of condoling with the Church, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the ruines ſhe ſuffers at the handes of the Pope. <hi>This griefe and ſadnes</hi> (ſay you, in the 10. page) <hi>did in wonderfull manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume me, and ſtill day by day, more and more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes me.</hi> Which wordes I could not read without ſmiling when I remember, how your fall giueth euidence againſt this your preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded pining away for ſorow. In your whole body from top to toe there appeare not any ſignes of the mortification of Chriſt Ieſus, nor of any inward griefe, either waſting your fleſh or drying vp your bones. When you write that you were in a conſumption by reaſon of ſadnes, I wonder whether you ſmiled not your ſelfe Nor is this any new fiction but the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mantell of Heretikes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>mor. ca.</hi> 19.</note> which S. <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> diſcouered longe ſince. <hi>Heretikes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make ſhew to condole with the Church, and with this ſayre ſhew of loue do they bayte their bookes of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:177851:52"/>deceyt.</hi> You weep the teares of the Crocodile, wherewith that rauenous beaſt moiſteneth and maketh ſlippery the ground, that when the paſſenger drawne by that counterfayt we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping approacheth, his feet fayle him, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly falleth a ioyfull pray to the mourner.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. Fourthly, you faigne that Scriptures fauour you in the fift page. <hi>Neuer</hi> (ſay you) <hi>did I at any tyme ſquare the motions and thoughts of my mind, by any other ruler, then ſuch as the Holy Ghoſt preſcribeth in Sacred Writ.</hi> This is ſoone ſaid: what Heretike ſaid it not? Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could their talking (ſaith S. <hi>Hierome</hi>) gayne them beleeuers, did they not make ſhew to confirme their peruerſe doctrine by diuine authority. You ſtill gouerned your thoughts &amp; inclinations by the rules of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, other ruler or direction you vſed neuer at any time. A great praiſe, which I cannot ſay agreeth to any of the Saints, if from that number we exempt Chriſt and his Virgin Mother. If this be true, ſurely you neuer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vnles one may ſinne, and do amiſſe in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the rule and gouernment of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: perchance you meane not ſo rudely as you write, and I can beleeue theſe your words may be more vayne then your mind. I only warne you not to be haſty to beleeue theſe thoughts and motions of the ſpirit, that preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to you, veſted with teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:177851:53"/>wherwith euen ſerpents are couered and walke about. Will you not beleeue me? then beleeue <hi>Luther,</hi> who writeth, <hi>they are wretches that do not conſider, that the Diuell doth dart ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous fiery thoughts into their hartes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Germ. wit. fol.</hi> 122. <hi>art.</hi> 552.</note> 
                     <hi>which be nothing els but moſt fine thoughts adorned with teſtimonies of Scripture, that they cannot perceaue the ſubtill poyſon that lurketh in them.</hi> Wherfore ſeing you make your boaſt of Scriptures, you might not wonder, though we ſhould anſwer you, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did the Manichees. <hi>Being bad, you read them not well, being ignorant you vnderstand them not right, being blind you cannot behold their truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. Fifthly, you pretend to follow the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>After the inward motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the holy Ghoſt only the holy Fathers</hi> (ſay you) <hi>haue beene the most honorable authors &amp; aduiſers of this my enterpriſe.</hi> You be not wiſe to trimme your ſelfe with the ſhew of a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient Fathers authority, ſeing you go towards thoſe Churches, that profeſſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>neither Fathers nor Mothers, but only the pure Word.</hi> And if you haue your Paſſe-port fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the auncient Fathers to leaue Rome, why haue you not alleadged ſo much as one cleere teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony out of them in your behalfe, and againſt the Roman Biſhops Preeminency?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi> 35.</note> You bring indeed out of the Councell of Carthage this teſtimony, which you call, <hi>the moſt renowned ſaying of the moſt renowned Cyprian. We do not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:177851:53"/>iudge any man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>nor remoue them from the right of communion that be of a contrary mind. For not any amongst vs doth make himſelfe the Biſhop of Biſhops, nor by tyrannicall terrour force his fellow-Biſhops to obey him.</hi> You could not <hi>(Antony)</hi> haue produced a cleerer teſtimony to conuince, that in truth you haue found no matter of ſubſtance in the Fathers, to obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was indeed moſt renowned for ſanctity, learning, and eloquence, but he was alſo renowned for an errour, which God permitted this worthy light of the Church to fall into. This errour he ſought by all meanes to eſtabliſh in that Councell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> out of which you bring this teſtimony: ſo finding in the approued writings of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> not any ſaying, that might ſteede you,
<note place="margin">Septem li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris de bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo.</note> you fly to the teſtimony of this erroneous &amp; reiected coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath by name confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a moſt renowned worke. And this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be the weightieſt authority of all that in ten yeares ſtudy you haue gathered. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer when you prayſe the charity, patience, &amp; wiſedome of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in his contention with Pope <hi>Stephen,</hi> depreſſing as much as you can the Pope, it is cleere, that hatred againſt the preſent ſucceſſour of <hi>Stephen,</hi> makes you forſake the knowne iudgment of antiquity. For S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a moſt moderate and friendly Cenſurer of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth ſay in plaine
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:177851:54"/>tearmes that in his contention with the Pope he wrote with ſo great indignation,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Baptiſ. c.</hi> 25</note> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this prudent aduiſe, <hi>that it were beſt not to mention all the things which Cyprian irritated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Stephen, powred forth in his anger, which brought with them danger of pernicious diſſention.</hi> Finally the words of S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſound more of indignation, then of any errour, nor do they croſſe the power of the Roman Biſhop in deciding the controuerſies of faith. For he doth not ſay, that none was in the Church ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt, whome the reſt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Biſhops were bound to obey, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with authority to put an end to the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies of faith; but he ſaith, that in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Carthage,</hi> there was not any Biſhop of Biſhops, nor any that did challenge to himſelfe ſuch authority: by which words he doth rather inſinuate, then deny the knowne authority &amp; title of the Roman Biſhop, though perchance he grudged and girded at the preſent exerciſe therof, accompting it Tyrannous, becauſe he found it oppoſed to his errour: which ſhews that S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> was then ouer feelingly moued againſt the Pope, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, who with great reaſon exclaimeth againſt you, and ſuch mates as would iuſtify their rebellion by <hi>Cyprians</hi> example <hi>Oh how deteſtable is their errour who thinke they do laudably imitate the faultes of ſome worthy men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>De vnico Bapt. cont. Petil. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> 
                     <hi>when they haue not any part of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:177851:54"/>their excellent Vertues.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fourth Gulfe,</hi> Mendacity againſt the Church.</head>
                  <p>NOTHING more notorious in former ages, nothing whereof the books of the Fathers do more ſound, then the impious mendacity of Heretikes, whereby they ſhew themſelues to be borne of him, that was <hi>falſe from the beginning, and the Father of falſhood.</hi> They put their confidence in vntruth, <hi>nor is there any man held for perfect amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt them</hi> (ſaith holy Irenaeus) <hi>that hath not fruclified and begot very great and mighty vntruths. Antony,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.</note> you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be perfect in your generation, and the fertility of your ſoile is ſufficiently proued by this little plant you now haue ſet forth, which is more ſtored with lies, then with leaues. Out of which multitude I will gather, and preſent you with ten, which be both notorious for their ſent, and very remarkable for their big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The firſt (whereof before we made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) but heere in the proper place to be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is ſet downe in your 15. pag. <hi>I ſaw now moſt cleerly, and did fully perceaue that at Rome, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any lawfull authority, yea by great violence &amp; wronge, innumerable new articles dayly were coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and obtruded vnto vs.</hi> If you marke well
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:177851:55"/>your owne wordes, perchance you your ſelfe will remaine amazed at the hugenes of this vntruth. You ſay, that doctrines new, cleerly falſe, without any ground, by extreameſt wrongfull violence, are euery day without number coined at Rome, and forced vpon the Church, euen as articles of faith. And yet you neither do, nor can name any article of the Roman faith, which hath not beene euer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained as a point of faith in former times, or els defined not in Rome, but in ſome gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. The ſecond vntruth in greatnes equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the firſt, in malice ſurpaſſeth it. This vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth ſtandes recorded in your 24. page, where you ſay, that you left the Church of Rome, &amp; ranne away, fearing <hi>the ordinary ſequells of hatred, that are, poyſoning, &amp; ſtabbing. For to this paſſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>matters are brought in this age, that at Rome, &amp; by authority fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome, the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies of the Church are committed no longer to Deuines, nor to Councells, but to racke-maiſters, to hang-men, to cut-throats, to bloud-ſuckers, to parricides.</hi> Here <hi>(Antony)</hi> you are ſeene to be in a fury, and to haue your hart imbued with the bloudy diſpoſition of the men you haue named. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe that which you hatefully charge her with, ſhe referred the Church-controuerſies of this age, not to be maintained with poyſoning &amp;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:177851:55"/>ſtabbing, by bloud-ſuckers, and parricides; but to be treated of, and decided by Fathers, by Biſhops, by graue and learned Deuines in the Councell of <hi>Trent.</hi> Such as obſtinatly defend doctrines accurſed by Councells, ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue the controuerſies that haue been already decided, ſuch men, I ſay, being conuicted of the crime, and confeſſing themſelues to be contemners of the Churches Councells, ſhe deliuers vp to be puniſhed, not to bloud ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, nor to Parricides, but to Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to the Iudges by them appointed: ſhe doth not reproue the endeauours of Deuines who diſcuſſe points of doctrine that are yet vndefined, but the temerity of Heretikes, <hi>whoſe labours are</hi> (as S. Leo ſaith) <hi>to ſeeke for the things that already are found,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 60.</note> 
                     <hi>to reuiue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies that are ended, to repeale the doctrines that haue byn formerly eſtabliſhed.</hi> You lay to our charge <hi>(Antony)</hi> the cruell demeanour of your <hi>Caluiniſts,</hi> who with ſwordes and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons do not defend Decrees of Councells which were laudable, do not put an end to controuerſies that were neuer before determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which were an euill not altogeather ſo vntolerable: but the doctrines that Councells haue builded, and ſet vp, they with their poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, ſwordes, and lances beate downe; the beliefe, which the tradition of Anceſtours, which the Decrees of generall Councells haue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:177851:56"/>rooted in Chriſtian breaſts, togeather with their bowells, they draw out, and caſt into the fire.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. The third vntruth is page 16. that <hi>We Romaniſts haue contracted the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, to which Chriſt promiſed the perpetuall aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the holy Ghost, to be the very Court of Rome.</hi> What Catholike euer wrote, ſpake, thought, or ſo much as dreamed of this fond conceite? The particuler Church of <hi>Rome</hi> we tearme the principall Church, with which all Churches muſt haue agrement and acceſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, in regard of her more powerfull Principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; we tearme the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the head of that Catholike Church, to which Chriſt promiſed perpetuall infallible aſſiſtance: but we ſay not, that the ſole Roman is the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Catholike Church, taking the Roman by it ſelf, without the reſt of the Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches adhering vnto her.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. The fourth vntruth is in the ſame 16. page, where you ſay that, <hi>It is exacted of vs, that we belieue firmely as an article of our Faith, that the whole ſpirit of Christ is reſident in the Court of Rome only, yea in the Pope only.</hi> What greater falſhood can be vttered or deuiſed? The ſpirit of Chriſt is indeed but one, nor is he in any one man, in whome he is not whole, if we reſpect his ſubſtance; and in this ſenſe we ſay that the ſpirit of Chriſt is whole in the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:177851:56"/>Pope, yea in euery Chriſtian. But this one and ſame ſpirit worketh very different and diuers things, according to which he is not whole in euery one; and in this ſenſe to ſay, that we beleeue the whole ſpirit of Chriſt to be abiding in the Pope only, is a great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth. Firſt the ſpirit of Chriſt aſſiſteth the Elect, whome through the dangerous miſeries of this life, he guideth by ſure meanes to the land of the liuing. Do we make this ſpirit reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Pope only? Do we not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that there be others Elect beſides the Pope? Secondly the ſpirit of Chriſt is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of adoption, in whome we crye <hi>Father, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Do we teach, that this ſpirit is in none but in Popes? that the Pope only is Iuſt, Holy, and the Sonne of God? Thirdly the ſpirit of Chriſt ſigneth and ſealeth the hartes of euery one that is faithfull, and annointeth them that they may belieue. And is this ſpirit alſo made by vs proper to the Pope only? Do we ſay that there is not any true beleeuing Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him? Fourthly, the ſpirit of Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth his Church ſo, that the whole Church can neuer erre. And do we not place this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit infallible in the whole Church? So that whatſoeuer hath byn in any age receaued by the vniforme beliefe of the whole Church, that without doubt as being a moſt certaine Chriſtian verity, we imbrace. Fiftly, the ſpirit
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:177851:57"/>of Chriſt decideth the controuerſies, which concerning faith, in euery age may ariſe in the Church; neither do we make faſt this ſpirit to the Pope only, but we teach that the ſame is abiding in the reſt of the Catholike Biſhops who be the Iudges of Faith, and togeather with the Roman Biſhop their Head, do deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine aſſuredly the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies of the Church. Wherefore I wonder where your forehead was, when you did not bluſh to write, <hi>that we make the whole ſpirit of Chriſt to be abiding in the Pope only.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. The fift vntruth is in the 26. page, <hi>That whatſoeuer hath byn formerly fortould by the Prophets, for the honour of the vniuerſall Church, we by extreme violence and wronge draw it all to the Roman Court only.</hi> It is certayne that ſome ſayings of Prophets do particulerly concerne the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and haue byn according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed in it. But that whatſoeuer is ſayd <hi>glorious of the Church in the ancient Prophets, we turne it all to the Church, yea to the Court of Rome only,</hi> you ſpeake it indeed in your ſplene againſt the Pope, but in ſpeaking it, your knowledge cannot chooſe but giue a checke to your tongue.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. The ſixt vntruth is, <hi>That the Roman Court hath now a longe while ſuppreſſed the holy Councells, &amp; ſo hath put out the eyes of the Church.</hi> If you ſpeake of the Councells that haue byn
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:177851:57"/>celebrated already, none do more Religiouſly obſerue their Decrees, then the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> If you meane of Councells that ſhould be gathered, that ſhe hinders that they cannot be now aſſembled; did not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (I pray you) call of late the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> to ſay nothing of Nationall, Prouincial, and Epiſcopall Councells, which are very frequently held? And if your accuſation be limited to General Councels, you muſt know that to gather ſo great and vniuerſall aſſembly is not an eaſy thing, nor neceſſary for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of euery hereſy, as S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſusduas Ep. Pelag. cap.</hi> 13.</note> 
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. You greeue I perceaue, that the Roman Biſhop is able to condemne you without a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell. Vnhappy were the Church, could he not do it. Out of pride innated to heretiks you ayme at this honour, that a Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the whole Church, ſhould be called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you; which glory alſo the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> as being moſt proud Heretikes, ſought, greiuing exceedingly that euery where by the Roman Biſhop, and others without any Generall Councell, they were condemned &amp; accurſed. <hi>They deſired</hi> (ſaith S. Auguſtine) <hi>a generall Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, that at leaſt they might trouble and diſquiet the Catholike world, ſeing they could not (God being againſt them) peruert it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="25">25. The ſeauenth Vntruth is in the 22. pag. <hi>That the Epiſcopall adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Biſhops, is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:177851:58"/>wholy periſhed, the whole gouernment of Churches is altogeather tranſlated to Rome, the Biſhops are ſcarſe the vicars and ſeruants of our Lord the Pope.</hi> That Church-buſines of moſt weight ſhould be referred to the Roman Biſhop, the Fathers in all ages haue ordayned. This is now adayes ſtill practiſed in the Church, what beſides and aboue this you add, is not the Roman cuſtome, but your ſlaunder.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. The eight, <hi>That Biſhops be ſubiect, not only to the Pope, Cardinalls &amp;c. but alſo to innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Religious Orders of Regulars, and to their Friars, who by their priuiledges deuoure and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp the power of Biſhops.</hi> Verily <hi>(Antony)</hi> you ſeeme to haue loſt all regard of your good name, that dare in this manner range without the bounds of truth.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. The ninth, <hi>That Catholike teachers, namely your maiſters the Ieſuites, do not furniſh their Diuinity with the ſayings of holy Scripture, exactly diſcuſſed and declared; that amongst them, and in the Church of Rome there is extreme igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Scripture.</hi> He that will but peruſe ſome Catholike writers in matters of ſacred lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſpecially the Ieſuites, will ſoone ſee how falſe a ſlaunder this is.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. The tenth, <hi>That the books of our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries are wholy concealed from vs, that ſuch as are excellent for their piety, and knowledge, yea the learnedſt Doctours or Biſhops we haue, are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:177851:58"/>in any ſort to read them.</hi> Thus you write, ſhewing that hatred againſt the Pope ſo tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports you, that you mind not what you ſay. How could the Catholiks of all nations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute your hereticall books, did none of vs read them? Are they in no ſort permitted, no not to the learnedſt of vs all? You may ſee <hi>(An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony)</hi> that though your booke be forbiden, yet I haue read it. Therfore S. Cyprian ſaith truly,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ep.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Amongst prophan men, that are departed from the Church, and from whoſe breaſts the holy Ghoſt is departed, what els is to be found, but a depraued mind, a deceitfull tongue, cankred hatred, and ſacrilegious lying? To which whoſoeuer giueth cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, ſhall at the day of iudgment be found to ſtand on their ſide.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The fifth Gulfe,</hi> Contumelious ſpeach againſt the Pope.</head>
                  <p>AFTER the Falſhood of Heretiks, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their railing, as being a neere neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour vnto it. <hi>Heretikes</hi> (ſayth S.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 16. <hi>mor. c.</hi> 14.</note> Gregory) <hi>with violency of words aſſayle the weake minds of the faithfull, and robbe the poore people. Not being able to ſupplant the learned, they take from the vnlearned the veyle of faith by their peſtiferous preaching.</hi> I ſhall not need <hi>(Antony)</hi> to ſearch into your booke for ſtormes of angry and rayling ſpeach, which in euery page meet
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:177851:59"/>with the Reader, and rage againſt the Pope, that ſo you may take from Catholikes the veyle of faith, by furious blaſtes of words, ſeing you can not with ſolide reaſons perſuade them to caſt it away. In the 16. page thus you thunder out againſt the Church of Rome. <hi>At Rome many thinges are made articles of Faith, which haue not any inſtitution from Christ, yea moreouer the ſoules of the faithfull be miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, and conſequently being blind, togeather with their blind guides, be lead, and fall headlong into the gulfe of Perdition.</hi> And in the 22. page you rage yet more angerly againſt Rome. <hi>It is not a Church</hi> (ſay you) <hi>but a Vineyard to make</hi> Noe <hi>drunke; it is a flocke which the Paſtour doth milke till bloud follow, which he pouleth, ſhaueth, fleaeth, and deuoureth.</hi> In the 32. page. <hi>It is not for Prophets to deale with the Roman Biſhop, that now doth ſo mainly trouble, ſcandalize, robbe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Church. The Maiesty of the Roman Pope is counterfayt, temporall, proude, vſurped, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="30">30. Finally your ſplene againſt this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pope moueth you to reuile the moſt holy Pope and Martyr S. <hi>Stephen.</hi> For in the 37. page you ſay, <hi>that S.</hi> Stephen <hi>out of indiſcreet zeale, by importune exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications, ranne head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into a miſcheiuous Schiſme; But Cyprian by his Patience, Charity, and exceeding great Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was the cauſe, that the ſeparation did not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:177851:59"/>enſue.</hi> This you charge the moſt holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, as though he had gone headlong into ſchiſme, a ſinne in your opinion much worſe then Hereſy. How wrongefully, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any iuſt cauſe? For no man could proceed more religiouſly, more modeſtly, and more prudently then Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> did in this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy with S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> When S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned mightily a doctrine, which (as he did not deny) was confirmed by the perpetuall cuſtome of the Church; what did this moſt holy Biſhop, appoynted of God to be Iudge, and to giue ſentence in this Controuerſy, where this perpetuall cuſtome of the Church was oppoſed againſt by the excellent learning and ſanctity of <hi>Cyprian?</hi> He ſhewed a reuerent reſpect to them both, as farre as truth &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would permit him. That the learning and ſanctity of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> might not ouerthrow a perpetuall cuſtome, without the aſſent of a generall Councell,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vincent. Lyrinenſ. com. c.</hi> 16.</note> he ſet out that Decree ſo much commended by the Fathers, <hi>Nihil inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uandum praeterquam quod eſt traditum.</hi> That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be innouated contrary to that which had byn deliuered by tradition. On the other ſide to ſhew the regard he had of S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> learning and ſanctity, he would not haue, that cuſtome ſhould ſo preiudicate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> doctrine, that thereupon it ſhould be accompted Heretical, before a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:177851:60"/>Councell, but that S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> though ſtil cleauing to his opinion, ſhould notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be retayned in the Catholike commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. A moſt prudent and temperate deciſion.</p>
                  <p n="31">31. Neither did he with any bitter ſpeach prouoke S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who yet (as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith) too much moued againſt Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> powred forth ſuch ſpeachs as it were better to bury them in obliuion then to record and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue them. Wherfore by the iudgment of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, not only truth ſtood on the Popes ſide, but alſo modeſty, charity, wiſedome in his proceedings for the defence of the truth. Take heed <hi>(Antony)</hi> that you be not a member of him,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 15.</note> 
                     <hi>to whome was giuen a wide mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king bigge things, and to blaſpheme the tabernacle of God, and the Saints that dwell in heauen.</hi> You are as good as your word: according to your promiſe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>de vtilitate credend. cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
                     <hi>you barke:</hi> But know, that you barke againſt that Church, <hi>which</hi> (as S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſaith) <hi>by ſucceſsion of Biſhops from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolike Sea, hath obteyned the height of authority, Heretikes her enemyes round about her, barking in vayne againſt her.</hi> Sampſon ſent foxes into the corne of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with their heads looſe, but with their tayles tied, <hi>which ſignifies,</hi> ſaith S. Hierome, <hi>that Heretikes haue tongues free to barke, but for performing, they be ſhackled and cumbred.</hi> They barke fiercely, but they beat but the ayre; ſooner may they breake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:177851:60"/>then fright and remoue the Roman Church from the imbracing of the faith, that hath byn deliuered vnto her. She cleauing to the diuine promiſes, as it were fixed in the firmanent, being on high, ſecure, deſpiſeth her rayling aduerſaryes, as the moone doth the dogges,
<q>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who barke, but winde drowneth their clamours baſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Diana chaſt holds on her heauenly pace.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſixt Gulfe,</hi> Arrogancy of Doctour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and Authority ouer the whole Church.</head>
                  <p>THE power which from the Roman Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop you would faine take, you challenge to your ſelfe, ſo making your ſelfe the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall curate of the Church in the 29. page. <hi>To euery Biſhop ſo is a particuler Church committed, that he muſt know, that alſo (when need is) the vniuerſall Church is by Chriſt commended to him.</hi> In the 30. page you add, <hi>that any Biſhop by his owne proper authority, may remoue to other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that are afflicted and oppreſſed.</hi> Thus you make a conueyance of power ouer the whole Church for your ſelfe, yet you do it ſubtilty, thinking you ſhould not be ſeen. You offer that vniuerſall power to euery Biſhop, knowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand that out of modeſty they will refuſe it, that ſo this authority reiected by the reſt,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177851:61"/>may retourne to your ſelfe, the firſt authour therof, as being properly and peculiarly yours. <hi>Yea</hi> (ſay you) <hi>it is moſt of all properly belonging to my office, to ſuccour (as farre as in me lieth) the Roman Court, that makes a ſchiſme and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by it ſelfe, and teareth in peeces the flocke of Chriſt.</hi> You are the new <hi>Atlas,</hi> you will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the Heauen, the vniuerſall Church with your ſhoulders. For which enterpriſe you thinke your ſelfe ſo ſufficient, that if the Pope and the reſt of Catholike Biſhops will yield to rely vpon your aduiſe, what will follow? <hi>I hope</hi> (ſay you) <hi>that ſhortly it will ſo fall out that full peace and concorde, and that ſo neceſſary vnion of the holy Churches will thereupon enſue, ſo that we ſhall beleeue all the ſame, and all abide in the ſame rule.</hi> Your hopes are vayne (poore ſoule) you take to much vpon you.</p>
                  <p n="33">33. Hereſies were before you were borne, and will be when you ſhalbe dead, &amp; the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Heretiks you now make greater by one through Pride, which deſerues to be pittied rather then confuted. For what? Put the caſe the Roman Biſhops would become your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and remit the buſines of vnion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation to your wiſedome; do you thinke the matter ended, and that the Sects oppoſite to the Roman Church, <hi>Grecians, Lutherans, Caluiniſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> will alſo without more ado become obedient to you at a becke? Such
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:177851:61"/>is your vanity, that you ſeeme not to doubt, but that all the reſt of Chriſtian companyes, beſides the Roman, will in this affaire of peace beare humble duty and reſpect towards you. You know not <hi>(Antony)</hi> and little do you imagine, what fierce, and furious windes, I meane proud and peremptory ſects rage in the Northern parts, which if you can aſſemble to a generall Councell, or keepe them when they are there in peace, verily you ſhall be more omnipotent then <hi>Aeolus.</hi> But afore-hand I tell you, they will not ſet a ruſh for you. Maydes and Boyes will laugh you to ſcorne, they will preferre their skil of Scripture before yours, with ſentences flowing thicke and threefold from their tongues, &amp; vttered with one breath, they will ouerload you. If you dare but mutter againſt what they ſay, you ſhall be ſtiled <hi>Papiſt;</hi> if you do not ſtraight yield to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them, they will take pitty of your eyes, that hauing beene ſo many yeares togeather accuſtomed to Popiſh darkeneſſe, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not now behold the cleere ſhining light of the Goſpel. This is the <hi>Caluinian</hi> nature, which if you be ignorant of, you will learne to your coſt.</p>
                  <p n="34">34. But to returne to the care of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church, which you preſumptuouſly take vpon you, togeather with authority, to viſit any Church at your pleaſure, which you ſhall iudge to haue need of your aſſiſtance.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:177851:62"/>Herein you commit a double errour. The firſt is, to thinke that a Biſhop, to help other Churches that are afflicted, may abandon his owne, and in ſuch manner adandon it, as to leaue it deſtitute of the meanes of ſaluation, to be rauened &amp; deuoured by wolues. For this in your conceit you do, and this you thinke that lawfully you may do, to ſuccour the Roman. But what ancient holy Biſhop can you name that did ſo? Which of them hath left written, that ſuch practiſe is laudable? Euen thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops whome you pretend to imitate, your ſelfe confeſſe, that they went to aſſiſt other Churchs, leauing their owne well appointed, and prouided of ſufficient perſons to teach and inſtruct them.</p>
                  <p n="35">35. The ſecond errour is, to thinke that euery biſhop at his owne good liking, and by his owne authority, may viſit other Churches that are in need, &amp; put them in order, though the proper Biſhops of ſuch Churches be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing. Which doctrine were it brought to practiſe, would breake and vtterly ouerthrow the peace and concord of the Church, as any man of iudgment may ſoone foreſee. For if euery Biſhop may, whenſoeuer he ſhall thinke it needfull, paſſe into the boundes of anothers Iuriſdiction, there ſit as Iudge of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies, and pronounce finall ſentence vpon them; it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, but Biſhops will very often encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:177851:62"/>and be beaten one againſt another by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſcord; nor can I imagine what other deuiſe can be thought of,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>de vnit. Eccleſ. c.</hi> 4.</note> or feigned ſo fit to trouble the quiet of Churches. <hi>There is</hi> (as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith) <hi>but one Biſhopricke, whereof a part is wholy poſſeſſed by euery one,</hi> yet ſo is the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke one, as the body of man is one, which hath an Head that commandeth the reſt of the members. In this manner the one Biſhopricke of the world hath one Sea, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme aboue the reſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 4.</note> which the ſame <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> tearmeth, <hi>the principall Sea, from which Prieſtly vnity and concord floweth, to which perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes can haue no acceſſe.</hi> The authority of this Sea ſpread and diffuſed ouer the reſt, is that <hi>Glew of concord,</hi> which ioyneth them all togeather in peace and charity. This Sea hath care to prouide for the neceſſityes of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church, and to ſend as Legats other Biſhops, whoſe Churches be well prouided, to giue ſuccour to others that are in need. By this Sea were <hi>Oſius, Athanaſius, Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of Vercells, <hi>Lucifer</hi> of <hi>Calaris,</hi> and others ſent, whome you name and affirme (but as your manner is without any proofe) that they put themſelues into the buſines of viſitation of Churches vpon their owne head, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
                  <p n="36">36. <hi>Theodoret</hi> writeth, <hi>that Lucifer Biſhop of Calaris, &amp; Euſebius Biſhop of Vercells, went about
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:177851:63"/>viſiting the Churches of the Eaſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>and namely the Churches of Antioch, and Alexandria, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Decrees of the Nicen Councell were kept. That Lucifer at Antioch, ordayned Paulinus Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, that Euſebius at Alexandria togeather with Athanaſius called a Councell, to which Lucifer ſent a Deacon, by whome he ſignified that he would agree to the things that, that Councell ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne.</hi> Theſe things you thinke that thoſe two Biſhops but of meane Seas, did performe by their owne proper authority, &amp; that you haue ſufficient authority of your ſelfe to do the like when, and wherſoeuer you ſhal iudge it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</hi>
                     </note> I may with reaſon exclayme with S. <hi>Auguſtine. What dares not the pride of rotten fleſh preſume?</hi> You ſhould <hi>(Antony)</hi> haue known what S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> writeth,
<note place="margin">Monod. in S. Baſil.</note> that <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Vercells,</hi> and <hi>Lucifer</hi> of <hi>Calaris</hi> were ſent <hi>ex vrbe Româ,</hi> from the Citty of <hi>Rome</hi> into the Eaſt, particularly to appeaſe a ſedition and tumult at <hi>Ceſaraea;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De viris il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtribus in Lucifero.</note> and that which S. <hi>Hierome</hi> left recorded of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that he was ſent Legat into the Eaſt to <hi>Conſtantius Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> from <hi>Liberius</hi> the Roman Biſhop. Whence you may gather that by power delegated to them from the Roman Biſhop, they were able to commaund the Eaſt, and ordaine ſuch great affaires, and not by their owne proper autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Wherefore you haue not <hi>Lucifer</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Calaris,</hi> but <hi>Lucifer</hi> prince of Pride for
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:177851:63"/>your patterne and preſident, when you go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to rayſe your ſelfe <hi>a throne in the coaſts of the North,</hi> that as Chriſt in the <hi>South</hi> by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> gouerneth the Vniuerſall Church, ſo in the <hi>North,</hi> he that ſeeks <hi>to be like to the higheſt,</hi> may by you, as Head, ſend forth and diſplay his counſells and deuiſes vpon all Chriſtendome.</p>
                  <p n="37">37. And what meant you to match your ſelfe with thoſe moſt holy and famous Biſhops &amp; Worthyes of the Church? Contrary things layd togeather deſerue to ſet forth mutually ech other. In the practiſe of theſe Saintes as in a glaſſe we may behold, how oppoſite all your proceedings are to the rules of ſanctity. They going left their Churches prouided, and well commended to other paſtours: You leaue your Church wholy deſtitute, to be deuoured (as you conceiue) by wolues. They either went to the Roman Church for ſuccour and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or were ſent by the Roman to giue ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and counſell to others: you fly from the Roman Sea, you deteſt &amp; blaſpheme it. They being men renowned in the whole Church for their learning and ſanctity, being earne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly inuited by diuers Biſhops, and by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſuffrages of the whole Church for that interpriſe deſigned, went to put an end to the Church Controuerſies: you being neither for the dignity of your Sea emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aboue the reſt,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:177851:64"/>nor commendable for Knowledge and Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life, a man vtterly vnknowne, who by your Apoſtaſy now beginne to haue fame: You, I ſay, offer your ſelfe for vniuerſal Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent and Curate to the world, which before this your offer had neuer ſo much as heard of your name. They laboured for that faith which had byn ſettled and defined by Councells: you ſeeke to bring in Doctrine which you know to haue byn many ages ago condemned by the authority of Councells. They ſtroue againſt Heretikes, that ſeing they had bin accurſed in Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cells, they might like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be reiected from the Catholike Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: your labours are in fauour of damned Heretikes, that though they be proſcribed by Councells, yet they may be reteyned in the Church, if ſo be, <hi>that they will profeſſe Chriſt, by the eſſentiall Creedes,</hi> as you ſpeake. And you ſeeme to be of the ſame mind, that ſome <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 48.</note> whome S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> condemns <hi>that it is no matter in what part or ſide a man be a Christian,</hi> nor do you conſider, <hi>that it is ſitting, that God ſhould be ſerued in vnity.</hi> Thus by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring your ſelfe with the ancient holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, your ſanctity appeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="gulf">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:177851:64"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The ſeauenth Gulfe,</hi> New flattering doctrine.</head>
                  <p>THIS Gulfe imbraceth two vices, and both of them properly belong to Heretiks: the one is to coyne new doctrines, the other to flatter their auditours, ſpecially Princes.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.</note> Of the firſt, S. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, <hi>That later Heretiks do day by day inuent ſome new thing, which neuer any man had thought of before.</hi> Of the ſecond S. <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Pelag.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That flattering properly agreeth to Heretiks, and to them that study how to deceaue ſoules, according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle: ſuch perſons ſerue not Christ our Lord, but their owne belly, and by ſweet ſpeaches and benedictions ſeduce the harts of the innocent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="39">39. Many new doctrines you haue in your booke, <hi>Antony,</hi> as are theſe. 1. That a Biſhop for feare of perſecution may forſake his flock, and leaue it wholy deſtitute. 2. That to euery Biſhop is giuen the care of the vniuerſall Church, ſo that by his owne proper authority he may intermeddle in the affaires of other Biſhoprikes. 3. That none who profeſſe Chriſt by the Creeds eſſential of the ancient Church, are to be repelled from the Catholike Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. 4. That Schiſme is a farre greater ſinne then Hereſy. Theſe your new conceits haue been mentioned and refuted already.</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:177851:65"/>
                  <p n="40">40. Other foure ſayings you haue, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you make fayre with Kings, by depreſſing the authority of the Church. The firſt is, <hi>That Kings can do many thinges in the Church.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>That the Church can do nothing at all in temporalls, ſpecially towards Kings.</hi> The third, <hi>That all iuriſdiction, is to be remoued from the Church.</hi> Theſe three propoſitions you haue in the 28. and 29. page. In the firſt, the Engliſh <hi>Parlame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarians</hi> agree with you. The two other be new, not only repugnant to the ancient Fathers, but alſo to the Heretikes of this age, to <hi>Puritans,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and to the eager defenders of the late Engliſh Oath. For theſe deny not the Churches authority ouer Kings, yea they graunt, that euen in temporalls the Church may commaund them, though they mantayne, that Kings obſtinate &amp; rebellious againſt the Church may not be depoſed from their gouernement. And what is <hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> but power to appoint what is right, to enact Lawes, to call the tranſgreſſors of their lawes before them, to ſit vpon them, and puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being conuinced of puniſhable offences? Now that the Church did in former times exerciſe this power, as deriued to her from Chriſt, is ſo cleere, that he that is ignorant therof, or ſo impudent as to deny it, I thinke him not worthy to be diſputed with.</p>
                  <p n="41">41. The fourth doctrine, I dare ſay is new
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:177851:65"/>and properly yours, then which ſcarſe any more baſe can be deuiſed to flatter Kings. Which doctrine you may ſeem to haue coyned of purpoſe, that therby you might make your ſelfe a free paſſage to the Court and Kitchin of the King of Great <hi>Britany.</hi> The doctrine is, that Kings, though they ſin, yet may not they be rebuked or checked, neither by their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liars, nor by Prieſts, nor by the cheefe Biſhop, but only by Prophets, whome God doth extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily raiſe &amp; deſigne for this office. That you teach this new Diuinity, I will conuince, and leaue you being conuinced to be iudged by his moſt Gracious Maieſty. The Roman Sage (were he to giue ſentence vpon you) would put you in the number of theeues, ſeing you ſeeke to depriue Kings of their beſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de beneficijs cap.</hi> 4.</note> whereof in Courtes there is euer great ſcarſity. <hi>I will ſhew you</hi> (ſaith Seneca) <hi>what is not be found in magnificent Pallaces, what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them that want nothing: they want one to tell the truth &amp; deliuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> errour the man that ſits amazed, &amp; beſides his wits in the mideſt of a great multitude of lyars, brought, by longe vſe of hearing pleaſing things inſteed of true things, to that paſſe, he knowes not what truth is.</hi> Such an admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher and rebuker of Chriſtian Kings, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Biſhop is by office deſigned by Chriſt, the greateſt treaſure he could beſtow on them, which you endeauour by your new Deuinity
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:177851:66"/>to take from them. For in the page 31. to proue that a Biſhop may reprehend and rebuke the Pope, you beginne to declare the matter by the difference that is betweene an earthly King, and the Pope, writing in this manner.</p>
                  <p n="42">42. <hi>The Maieſty of an earthly King is to be dreaded, who, as</hi> Tertullian <hi>ſaith, is ſecond to God, inferiour to God only; and ouer whome, ſaith</hi> Optatus, <hi>none is but God only. Wherefore when</hi> Dauid <hi>was to be rebuked for his adultery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, not the High-prieſt, nor any other, either Prieſt or Leuite, not any man either friend or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar, durst aſſume to himſelfe that office: But God himſelfe for this purpoſe, appoynted his owne proper and peculiar meſſenger, and ſent the Prophet</hi> Nathan <hi>to reprehend the King. But for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Biſhop now moſt of all troubling, ſcandalizing, robbing and ſpoyling the Church, it is not for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to deale with him, it is not to be expected that God ſhould ſtirre vp for this enterpriſe ſingular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, nor ſend ſpeciall meſſengers. The Maieſty of our Roman Pope is not ſo great, that it ought to feare vs; that temporall ſtately Maieſty is counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faite, vſurped, no Maieſty at all; the Pope he is our brother, our Colleague, a Biſhop as we are.</hi> All theſe be your owne words <hi>(Antony,)</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you breath forth that flattering doctrine which I layd to your charge. You ſay the Popes Maieſty ought not ſo to terrify Biſhops, but they may rebuke him. But the Maieſty of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:177851:66"/>an earthly King is ſo dreadfull, ſo much to be feared, that no man that is not a Prophet, though he be the chiefe Biſhop, may take v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him the office to reprehend him. Do you ſpeake this of baſe feare which Cowardes beare towards them that haue power ouer the body, or of pious feare and reuerence which by right is due to Superiours; which if we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, we do againſt our Duty, and offend God? If you ſpeake of the firſt kind of feare, you faigne a difference betweene the Pope and the King, where there is not any at all.</p>
                  <p n="43">43. For as the Popes Maieſty ought not to ſtrike into our harts baſe and ſeruile feare, which makes vs to neglect our dutyes: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ought not to be in this manner affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghted by Kingly Maieſty, Chriſt hauing giuen vs an expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment not to feare them, <hi>that kill the body, but can do no hurt to the ſoule.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 16.</note> And <hi>de facto,</hi> as the King by the terrour of his Maieſty may fright men vniuſtly, and make them not to diſcharge towards him the duty that they owe of correction; ſo may the Pope alſo; for elſe why ran you away? Why fly you the Popes paynted Maieſty, paynted Priſons, paynted ſires, paynted torments? You be not ſo farre beſides your ſelfe: ſo that this feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullnes of the Kings Maieſty aboue the Popes is deuiſed without any ground, ſpeaking of baſe and ſlauiſh feare. For this ſort of feare, as
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:177851:67"/>neither of their Maieſtyes ought, ſo either of their Maieſtyes may ſtrike into baſe minded mens harts. You ſpeake then (if you ſpeake to the purpoſe) of pious reuerence and feare of Superiours, due by right vnto them, and therein you put the difference betwixt the Kings Maieſty and the Popes. So you ſay that the Popes Maieſty ought not of right to be ſo feared, but that Biſhops may freely rebuke him: but the Kinges Maieſty by right and by the Law of God ought to be ſo dreaded, that no man may reprehend him, no not the Pope, except he haue a Propheticall and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary commiſſion to do it. Whence it is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that none may without ſinne tell Kings of their faultes that be not Prophtes.</p>
                  <p n="44">44. Now how vngodly and abiect this your new conceyte is, may ſoone appeare by conſidering the arguments you bring to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it. They are three contayned in your former words, and deriued from three diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which you imagine betweene the Pope and the King. The firſt is, That the Popes Maieſty is <hi>counterfayte, temporall, faigned, no Maieſty at al;</hi> but the Maieſty of a terrene King is exceeding great <hi>(tremenda)</hi> to be dreaded and feared: therfore the Popes Maieſty may and ought to be freely rebuked, but the Kings Maieſty in no caſe, not for any cauſe, nor by any man that is not ſpecially ſent of God for
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:177851:67"/>that purpoſe. This diuerſity betwene terrene and ſpirituall authority, you proue not. And no meruayle: you found it not out by reaſon, but by reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that ſpirit, which is prince ouer men, <hi>that mind earthly things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Philip. c.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſe belly is their God, whoſe glory in their owne confuſion.</hi> By the ſame ſpirit was <hi>Luther</hi> moued to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the ſtate of Virginity with the ſtate of Marriage, writing,
<note place="margin">In epiſt. ad Cor.</note> 
                     <hi>that the firſt ſtate is heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, ſecular, terrene, mirery; the ſecond ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, heauenly, diuine, golden.</hi> This doctrine fleſh and bloud reuealed to <hi>Luther,</hi> which alſo moueth you to debaſe Prieſtly Maieſty vnder the feete of earthly. In the palate of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient holy Biſhops, Prieſtly dignity had a more diuine ſauour, they had it in higher eſteeme, which they did ſo farre extoll aboue Royall, as the heauen ſurmounted the earth, the ſpirit goeth beyond the fleſh. <hi>You,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. ad Praeſid. iraſ.</note> 
                     <hi>O earthly Princes</hi> (ſaith one of them) <hi>the law of Chriſt maketh ſubiect to our bench, we likewiſe haue power and commaund, yea power more excellent and eminent then yours is, vnleſſe it be reaſonable that the ſpirit ſhould yield homage to the fleſh, &amp; heauenly things giue place to earthly things.</hi> Behold what an high conceit theſe pious Prelates did frame of their Pontificall power? You to whome <hi>power to binde both in Heauen and Earth,</hi> in reſpect of earthly power ſeemeth <hi>vnſauory</hi> and <hi>contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible;</hi> what wonder though as <hi>ſalt without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour,</hi>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:177851:68"/>you were caſt forth vnto the dung-hill.</p>
                  <p n="45">45. The ſecond difference betweene the King and the Pope deuiſed by you, is, that the Pope is <hi>the brother and colleague of Biſhops,</hi> but the King <hi>is ſecond after God, inferiour to God only.</hi> By the firſt, becauſe the Pope is the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Biſhops, you inferre, that the Pope may be rebuked by his fellow biſhops. And your inference is good, if the Pope giue iuſt cauſe, if the correction be giuen with due modeſty, in due time, place and manner, that it may be for the good both of the Pope &amp; the Church. By the other, becauſe the King <hi>is ſecond to God,</hi> you gather that no man may rebuke him but God only, and the Prophets that are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp by God, &amp; ſent purpoſely for that end. You be then of this mind, that the dignity of a King which is to be next vnto God; doth make him not to be the ſonne of the Church, nor the brother of Chriſtians. For if his being ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme after God in temporalls, hinder not but that in ſpirituall things he is the ſonne of the Church, why may he not be rebuked by his Mother? If he be the brother of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the brother of the Children of the Church, why may not they warne him of his faults, freely yet with modeſty, with prudency, and with Charity?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.8.</note> The Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>What ſon is it whom the Father doth not correct? If you be not vnder diſcipline and correction, you be not ſonnes, but ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards.</hi>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:177851:68"/>You can neuer exempt the King from being vnder the diſcipline and correction of Biſhops, except you put him from the number of the children of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="46">46. But take heed you do not this, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therein you ſhould contradict the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers (for to do that, you would not greatly care) but for feare leaſt you offend his gratious Maieſty of <hi>Great Brittany,</hi> whome by this flattering diuinity you endeuour to ſooth. For <hi>William Tooker</hi> Deane of <hi>Lich-field</hi> in his booke called <hi>Duellum aduerſus Martinum Beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> in the 34. page thereof, hath theſe words. <hi>Our moſt gracious and potent King Iames doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt nothing more glorious, and more honorable for him, then with Valentinian to profeſſe himſelfe the ſonne of the Church, and with Theodoricus King of Italy moſt willingly to acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the pupill of the Church, and the diſciple of his Arch-biſhops and Biſhops.</hi> Marke me <hi>(Antony.)</hi> Either you deny the King to be the ſonne of the Church, or you grant it. If you deny it, you take from the King the title which (if we beleeue <hi>Maiſter Tooker</hi>) moſt, and aboue all other he eſteemeth. If you grant the King to be the ſonne of the Church, and yet will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt him from being vnder her diſcipline, you make him (if we beleeue S. <hi>Paul</hi>) not a lawfully begotten ſonne, but adulterous. Which way ſo euer you turne your ſelfe, you
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:177851:69"/>are in bryars; you both diſpute impertinently, and flatter fooliſhly.</p>
                  <p n="47">47. The third difference you put between the Pope and the King is, <hi>that it is not for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets to meddle with the Pope,</hi> but to reprehend Kings, God himſelfe <hi>appoints ſpeciall meſſengers, and Prophets.</hi> This difference you proue by the example of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who when he was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked for murder and adultery, no man, no not the High-prieſt himſelfe durſt attempt it, becauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> being King, was inferiour to God only. Heere you ſuppoſe things that are falſe, &amp; yet were your falſe ſuppoſalls granted you, yet your argument is naught. Firſt it is falſe that <hi>Dauid</hi> was to be rebuked for adultery and murder. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſinned cloſely, he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly made away with <hi>Vrias</hi> by the ſworde of his enemyes. This his wickednes mortall men could hardly know, much leſſe could they reproue him for it. Secondly it is falſe that the high-prieſt durſt not reprehend <hi>Dauid,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a King next vnto God. He rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him not, becauſe he knew not that he was worthy of rebuke: for had he knowne it, why might he not haue dared to do that to <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral. cap.</hi> 26.</note> which <hi>Azarias</hi> High-prieſt did to King <hi>Ozias,</hi> whome after ſharpe reprehenſions he turned out of the Temple? And how vaine your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is, though your premiſſes were ſolide, hence may it appeare, that by the ſame kind of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:177851:69"/>argument, I will eaſily proue, that the Pope may not be rebuked, but by ſome Prophet and ſpeciall meſſenger ſent for that purpoſe from God. For God, to reprehend the High-prieſt hath ſent ſpeciall meſſengers.
<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note> When <hi>Hely</hi> the High-prieſt out of fond affection and indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence towards his ſonnes, permitted them to ſtaine the worſhip of God with moſt heynous and ſcandalous ſinnes, and ſo deſerued to be rebuked and ſoundly tould of his fault; yet none of the Prieſts, nor of the Leuites, nor of his friends and familiars durſt (that we read of) rebuke him for it; but God ſent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Prophets and ſpeciall Heraldes for that purpoſe. Therfore the high Prieſt may not be rebuked, but of Prophets, &amp; by ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God. This argument is much ſtronger then yours is, yet if I ſhould ſeriouſly bring it, as placing any force therein, I were a foole. But you that would haue earthly power preferred before the heauenly, what wonder though your arguments in this behalfe be earthly?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="gulf">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The eight Gulfe,</hi> Fond and idle Talking.</head>
                  <p>YOvv write in the 28. page, <hi>that you heare a voice which doth thunder ſtill in your eares, and ſay vnto you, Cry.</hi> You follow the inſtinct
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:177851:70"/>of this voice;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Iſa.</hi>
                     </note> you do as Heretikes vſe to do, <hi>whoſe doctrine,</hi> ſaith S. Hierome, <hi>conſiſtes not in knowledge, but in clamors; and in idle multiplicity of words without ſenſe.</hi> You powre forth words and make a noiſe, wherewith you beate the ayre, and touch no body; yea ſometimes you ſtrike your ſelfe, with one ſentence deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what in another you had ſet vp. Examples in both kinds of this fond talking are very plentifull in your booke, I ſhall gather you a few.</p>
                  <p n="49">49. In the 35. page, being now Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Vniuerſal Church, created by your owne authority, you very grauely exhort and rebuke the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Biſhops in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner. <hi>Articles in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues indifferent that were neuer yet in the Church ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly diſcuſſed, eſtabliſhed or defined, let vs not admit as articles of fayth, except they be first ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently defined to the full, or be ſhewed to be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently already defined. Let vs not alſo condemne any for Heretikes, except it be first cleare, that they haue been formerly, or now are ſufficiently condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Church. In things indifferent then, let free ſcope be left to euery one, to thinke and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe as they pleaſe: let euery one abound in their owne ſenſe, till the Church, taught and gouerned by the ſpirit of Christ, ſhall make an end of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, and ſeparate the true chaffe from the true grayne.</hi> Thus you talke. And to what
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:177851:70"/>end are ſo many wordes caſt into the wind? Whome do they concerne? Who requires that doctrines queſtionable be admitted as articles of Faith, before they be fully and ſufficiently defined? Who would haue any to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Heretikes, before the Church inſtructed by the holy Ghoſt hath-cenſured them? We Catholikes hold the Primacy of the Roman Biſhop as a doctrine of Faith: the denyers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of who haue byn accurſed in diuers generall Councells we deteſt as Heretikes. This grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you, ſo many Councells be not full, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you the Paſtour forſooke of the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church, haue not ſubſcribed vnto them. And in the 38. page you thunder againe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any bolt, and giue vs idle preſcripts. <hi>Let vs</hi> (ſay you) <hi>hold different doctrines, let vs be of contrary opinions, till things be fully defined which are not yet fully defined, but in the meane time let vs continue in vnity. Do not make the ſchiſme grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then it is.</hi> Thus you idly ſpend pen, inke and paper. What doctrine do we demaund that you ſhould beleeue, which hath not byn eſtabliſhed by the Decrees of general Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels. Well ſaith Marcian the Emperour, <hi>that they call in queſtion, and dare publikely diſpute againſt that which is already iudged and rightly ordayned; offer great wronge to the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the moſt Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Synodes.</hi> The doctrine which moſt you miſlike, to wit, that the Pope is appoynted of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:177851:71"/>God, Head and Paſtour of the whole Church, the Orient and Occident hath defined in nine Generall Councells. What fuller Councells can you deſire? Are you yet fully ſatisfied? No: but you puffe, and go forward blowing &amp; ſtill demanding fuller definitions, till you come to conclude your Pamphlet with this ſentence, which to me ſeemes wholy deuoyd of any good ſenſe. <hi>Let vs driue away, by the light of the truth Euangelicall, without firme ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, the darkenes of errours and falſities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="50">50. Secondly that you not only beate the ayre with idle words, but alſo fight againſt your ſelfe, denying in one place what in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you affirme, theſe fiue examples of your contradictions may make manifeſt.</p>
                  <p n="51">51. The firſt contradiction. In the page 8. and 9. you ſay, that the Roman diligence in forbidding the bookes of her aduerſaries did euer diſpleaſe you. <hi>This practiſe</hi> (ſay you) <hi>not to be voyd of ſuſpition, as reaſon doth ſhew, ſo did I euer Iudge.</hi> Euer, <hi>Antony?</hi> did you neuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the reading bookes that impugne the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doctrine? did you neuer aboue meaſure deteſt it? In the 4. page to proue that you tooke not your reſolution to depart from vs, by reading our aduerſaries bookes, thus you write. <hi>I Religiouſly call God to witneſſe, that I did vehemently abhorre from the reading of the bookes, that the Roman diligence had forbidden.
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:177851:71"/>Which bookes if any Prelate addicted to the Roman Court hath deteſted, then I by reaſon of vayne feares conceaued againſt this reading in my child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, did aboue meaſure deteſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="52">52. The ſecond Contradiction. In the 9. page you ſay, That you ſtill ſuſpected the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, by reaſon of her forbidding of her aduerſaries bookes, <hi>that her doctrine was weake, and not able to ouerthrow her aduerſaries arguments.</hi> But in the 7. page you ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, to wit, <hi>that the proper decrees &amp; doctrines of Rome, were with true captiuity of your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding wholy imprinted, and rooted in your mind.</hi> How were they wholy imprinted in your mind, if you euer ſupected them? if you ſtill imbraced them, not without feare &amp; ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering?</p>
                  <p n="53">53. The third Contradiction. You ſay in the 2. and 5. page, That by going from Rome, <hi>you incurre great loſſe of wealth and dignity.</hi> And in the 25. page, <hi>That vnder the Pope you had honorable dignities, and commodities not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned.</hi> But in the page 22. you ſay, that, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops vnder the Pope that are not Temporall Lords</hi> (and ſuch a meere Biſhop were you) <hi>are ſcarſe ſo much as ſeruantes of our Lord the Pope, baſe, contemptible, oppreſſed, troden vnder foote, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſubiect.</hi> Now <hi>(Antony)</hi> make theſe things agree, <hi>baſe ſeruitude and honorable dignity, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dityes not to be contemned, &amp; miſerable ſubiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:177851:72"/>
                  <p n="54">54. The fourth contradiction. In the 22. page you write, <hi>That the Church vnder the Pope, is no Church, but a certaine Common-wealth vnder his Monarchy, meerly temporall.</hi> Theſe wordes import that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no Church: but elſe where you call it a Church, yea the Church of Chriſt. Pag. 29. <hi>I am Biſhop in the Church of Chriſt,</hi> who then were Biſhop in no Church but in the Roman. And in the 35. page, you call the Roman Biſhops, <hi>your Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leages and fellow-Biſhops.</hi> And againe page 39. you thus commaund the Catholike-Roman Biſhops, <hi>Offer your communion readily to all, that ſtill retayne their opinions againſt you, yet ſo, that falſityes be driuen away.</hi> None can make that common with another, which they haue not themſelues. If the Roman Church be not a Chriſtian Communion and ſociety, how can they offer readily their Chriſtian Society and communion to others? If it be meerely and wholy a temporall Common-wealth, what can it affoard to her friends but meere human peace and temporall communion?</p>
                  <p n="55">55. The fifth Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradiction. In the 39. pag. you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand Biſhops, <hi>to reſtore peace and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to all that profeſſe Chriſt by the Creeds eſſentiall.</hi> In theſe words you require no more, then the profeſſion of the Creeds eſſentiall, but within three lines after this ſentence followes: <hi>Offer readily your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion to all, ſauing their opinions,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:177851:72"/>yet driuing away falſityes.</hi> Here you will haue them that communicate togeather, to agree not only in the profeſſion of your eſſentiall Creeds, but alſo in the abnegation of falſities, wherof you expreſſe neither the quality nor the number. And yet alſo herein you agree not with your ſelfe: for in the 36. page you praiſe S. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> becauſe <hi>he did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with ſuch as erred, and whome he iudged to erre moſt grieuouſly.</hi> Here you will haue errours to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, and communion not to be broken for errours: but in the former ſpeach you allow not communion, but with this condition, that on both ſides falſities be driuen away. I demand of you <hi>(Antony)</hi> whether errours &amp; grieuous errours be not falſities? If they be: then how is communion to be giuen without reiecting of errours, and yet not to be exhibited with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out driuing away falſities? Here you ſhamful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contradict your ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>I will now end. I haue ſhewed who you were before you fell, and by what ſtepps and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees you came to fall into the depth of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſy. I haue alſo declared who now you are, and into what a low gulfe of Hereticall Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety you be plunged. Why then may I not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and in few wordes foretell, what will finally become of you, laying vpon you the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:177851:73"/>Cenſure of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timoth. c.</hi> 3.9.</note> 
                  <hi>You ſhall not further proceed, for your folly ſhall be manifest vnto almen.</hi> You being thus diſcouered by this <hi>Suruey,</hi> if you will not ſee your ſelfe, yet Proteſtants wil eaſily ſee who you are, and what great want of iudgment you haue bewrayed in your wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. They will wonder that into ſo little a Pamphlet written in your owne defence, you could poſſibly lay togeather on a heape, ſo many things openly falſe, abſurd, impious, ſo many things wherein you contradict your ſelfe, wherein you bewray the courſes which you would fayne haue hidden, wherin you vtterly ouerthrow your owne cauſe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you <hi>can neuer proceed further,</hi> except you returne backe to the Catholike Church, from which you haue fayled. You are gone out of the way, you muſt needs returne before you can make forward.</p>
               <p n="56">56. The applauſe wherwith our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries intertained you, let it not detayne you from this returne. Therein they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ſwarueth from the nature of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, or from the courſe that ancient Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes held.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Praeſc. cap.</hi> 40.</note> 
                  <hi>Being themſelues Apoſtata's</hi> (ſaith Tertullian) <hi>they ioyfully receaue our Apoſtata's that fly vnto them, they beſtow on them benefices, they aduance them to dignities; ſo tying them faſt to their ſect by honours whome they cannot bind ſure to them by the truth.</hi> Nor let their exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:177851:73"/>prayſes, predictions allure you, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſhew their great hope conceyued, that they ſhall vanquiſh the Pope, you being their leader. Theſe are but bubbles &amp; froath which your fall from ſo high a ſtate, into ſo deep a gulfe hath rayſed, &amp; ſuddaynly will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away. Deſpiſe them. Theſe are <hi>the oyle of ſinners,</hi> wherewith wretches appointed for fire euerlaſting, be in this world anointed, that in the next their burning may be the ſorer. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre them. Theſe are but conceits, prayſes wherwith they make a vaine ſhew of triumph ouer vs, and flatter you to your face, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind your backe play vpon you with ſcoffes, loading you with the diſgracefull titles you truly deſerue, and with ſome alſo which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance you haue not merited; when not long ago at S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> you made a ſpeach in the ſtreet, do you not know, what the people then preſent vttered againſt you? They called you great-bellied-Doctour, made fat vnder Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; and ſome there were alſo that ſayd, that before you ranne away from the Pope, you got your owne Neece with child, and that feare to be puniſhed for it, made you trudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with your great load of fleſh in ſuch haſt.</p>
               <p n="57">57. I do not relate theſe things as beleeuing them, or as deſiring that they ſhould be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but to ſhew how vaine be the prayſes of Heretikes, &amp; how vayne a prophet you were
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:177851:74"/>in promiſing to yourſelfe, <hi>that your moſt beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sara</hi> (for ſo you tearme your good Name) <hi>ſhould, remaine pure and vntoucht in the mideſt of Barbarians.</hi> For theſe things were vented a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, not in <hi>Rome</hi> by Catholikes, but in <hi>London</hi> by Proteſtants, openly in the ſtreets. Many great Perſonages alſo do not ſticke to mutter about you, that beſides groſſnes of body you haue brought nothing with you, that is anſwerable to the greatnes of your titles; that your booke doth not equall the ſolemne oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and expectation you haue raiſed therof; that you do not performe therein what you promiſe; yea ſome would not haue it printed at all, fearing you may therwith diſgrace your ſelfe and their Ghoſpell.</p>
               <p n="58">58. Now then <hi>(Antony)</hi> why tarry you <hi>in the middest of a depraued and peruerſe nation?</hi> Why do you wretchedly draw on your gray hayres with grief and diſgrace to your graue? Seeke for true renowne, who haue loſt the vaine honour that you hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for irreligiouſly. <hi>Enter into your owne hart, remember whence you are falne, do pennance, and turne againe to your firſt workes.</hi> Through Gods goodneſſe aſſiſting you, rayſe your ſelf a monument of the diuine mercy, which this preſent age, which the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times may admire, and make a laſting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of. Let reioycing poſterity to the worlds end, be taught by your example this comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:177851:74"/>truth, that the bowels of diuine benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be not ſo loathing of ſinners, but that they willingly take in againe, euen tepide Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata's, whome they were forced to caſt vp. Ayme at the dignity of a Penitent, ſeeing you haue loſt the ſtate of Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. You that haue let go the ſterne; you who beaten out of the ſhip wherein you were Pilot, floate in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, lay hold on this board which is reached vnto you, whereon you may ſwimme to a Kingdome. You are threeſcore yeares old ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry nigh, the remnant of your yeares be bad, and few. Withdraw theſe your bad yeares from vice, that you may ſee <hi>good dayes.</hi> Beſtow theſe your few yeares in pennance, that you may gaine <hi>yeares eternall.</hi> Let not the bitternes of penna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce diſcourage you, which by the dew of diuine Comforts falling from aboue will be ſweetned: <hi>Where ſinne hath abounded, there grace will more abound.</hi> The deeper and darker that the dungeon is wherin you are kept, by ſo much more ſweet will the breath be, that being thence deliuered, you ſhall draw, <hi>in the lightſome mercies of your Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="59">59. Nor let it deiect you, that you haue ſhamefully falne, but remember that as the depth of the diuine Iuſtice, ſo likewiſe the depth of the diuine Mercy is vnſearchable. <hi>Who knowes the mind of God?</hi> And whether he hath not ordayned, that this your fall be for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:177851:75"/>your owne riſing againe, and for the riſing of many? The ſecret pride wherein you went mounting a loft in your conceyts againſt your Creatour, was to be beaten downe by a mighty thunderclappe, that you &amp; others might feele it. For this your pride ſtanding on foote, you could no wayes be ſaued by him, <hi>that lookes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon low things, &amp; high things knoweth a farre off.</hi> Wherfore I am not greeued with your defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, no not for your owne ſake, which yet would grieue me, could I be perſuaded, that you ſhould haue byn ſaued, had you continued in the Catholike Church. But when I conſider the wauering diſpoſition, the darke and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled proceedings of Apoſtata's both an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and new, I come to be ſetled in this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That none periſh by falling from the Church, who would not as well haue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed through their ſecret &amp; concealed errours, though they had continued outwardly in the Church. And theſe men are by the ſecret courſe of diuine Prouidence caſt out of the Church, to the end that being ſo forlorne, they may reflect on themſelues, or elſe that by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Church, they may benefit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who by remayning in the Church would neuer haue benefited themſelues. This to me ſeemes the opinion of S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> whoſe golden words I here ſet downe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>de vera Relig. c.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Seing it is truly ſayd, that Hereſies muſt needs be, to the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:177851:75"/>end that they who are of proofe amongst you, may be made manifeſt, let vs make vſe of this benefit of the diuine prouidence. For Heretikes be made of ſuch kind of men, who though they were in the Church, would we neuertheleſſe erre: but being out of the Church they be very beneficial, not becauſe they teach the Truth, for hereof they are ignorant, but becauſe they awake carnall Catholikes to ſeeke, and ſpirituall Catholikes to declare the truth.</hi> Thus S. Auguſtine.</p>
               <p n="60">60. I could name diuers Apoſtata's with whome in times paſt I haue byn acquaynted, who euen then, when to others, yea to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they ſeemed Catholikes, were couertly infected with Errours againſt the Roman Faith, and poſſeſſed with ſecret malice againſt the Roman Sea. But you <hi>(Antony)</hi> are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this truth that may ſtand inſteed of many. For (to ſay nothing of your open eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt the Roman doctrine in your laſt ten yeares) you that ſtill beleeued, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was iuſtly ſuſpected of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, what could the externall ſhew and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of a Roman Catholike haue auayled you to ſaluation? You that ſtill were doubting whether ſome doctrine more firme then the Catholike, did not lye hidden in the writings of Heretikes; what good would it haue done you, that you kept your eyes from their books, &amp; your body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Conuenticls? You had
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:177851:76"/>periſhed ſecretly, nor (ſuch was your care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſnes) had you perceaued that you did pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Now you erre openly, that many may be taught the truth; you periſh in the ſight of the world, that diuers affrighted with your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, may be moued to work their ſaluation. And why may not this your fall, turne to your euerlaſting exaltation? I will not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre, but when you haue been cloyed with the huskes of ſwine, which now you feed in a farmers houſe, that once were a feeder of ſheep in the Church: I do not deſpayre, I ſay, but that one day you will call to mind the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of your fathers houſe, and hauing learned by deare experience what a miſchiefe ſecret Pride is, retourning to the Catholike Church, you will ſay, <hi>I had periſhed, vnleſſe I had periſhed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:177851:76"/>
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the Printing.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Page</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Line</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Fault</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Correction.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>vlt.</cell>
                     <cell>of</cell>
                     <cell>out of</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>9.</cell>
                     <cell>hell in</cell>
                     <cell>hell; in</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>vnion.</cell>
                     <cell>vnion?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>your</cell>
                     <cell>our</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>penult.</cell>
                     <cell>falſe</cell>
                     <cell>falne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>of</cell>
                     <cell>if</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>21.</cell>
                     <cell>vnto men</cell>
                     <cell>vnto you</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>25.</cell>
                     <cell>23.</cell>
                     <cell>now as this</cell>
                     <cell>now this</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>26.</cell>
                     <cell>5.</cell>
                     <cell>proſecuteth</cell>
                     <cell>perſecuteth</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>31.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>begon</cell>
                     <cell>be gone</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33.</cell>
                     <cell>14.</cell>
                     <cell>do be</cell>
                     <cell>to be</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>53.</cell>
                     <cell>3.</cell>
                     <cell>to, rather</cell>
                     <cell>to. Rather</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>your ſelfe. You</cell>
                     <cell>your ſelfe, you</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>deeds. You</cell>
                     <cell>deeds, you</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>67.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>Church.</cell>
                     <cell>Church?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>world.</cell>
                     <cell>world?</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>68.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>guide</cell>
                     <cell>grudge</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>72.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>ſwarueth</cell>
                     <cell>ſwarued</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>79.</cell>
                     <cell>19.</cell>
                     <cell>one</cell>
                     <cell>owne</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>98.</cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>fall</cell>
                     <cell>face</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>102.</cell>
                     <cell>2.</cell>
                     <cell>ſo</cell>
                     <cell>to</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>111.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                     <cell>are</cell>
                     <cell>were</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>121.</cell>
                     <cell>12.</cell>
                     <cell>deſerue</cell>
                     <cell>do ſerue</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
